<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Zhe Song&#39;s International Blog</title>
  <subtitle>宋哲的国际博客，微信公众号songzheglobal</subtitle>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="http://zhesong.info/"/>
  <updated>2017-07-15T09:28:27.000Z</updated>
  <id>http://zhesong.info/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Zhe Song</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>《军师联盟》今日收官</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2017/07/14/junshi-lianmeng/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2017/07/14/junshi-lianmeng/</id>
    <published>2017-07-14T12:07:01.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T09:28:27.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/junshilianmeng.jpg" alt=""><br>周末，聊个电视剧，就是今天刚刚收官的《军师联盟》，最近热播的三国题材电视剧。</p>
<p>我最早在春节之前看了预告片，就列入今年的看片计划，一直在关注。</p>
<p>视角<br>这部剧很有新意，最大的特点是它的视角，是从司马懿的角度展开的。旧三国、新三国都是用的上帝视角展开剧情，也常有作品用的是关羽视角。作为一个反派角色，司马懿的视角还是第一次见。<br>司马懿的视角是个不错的选择，因为他是三国最大的赢家，实现了统一，开启了以风度和名士著称的晋朝。讲他的故事，观众会看的很爽，因为他的日子是一天天越来越好的。而三国演义是以刘备诸葛亮为主线的，在蜀国成立后就一天不如一天了，观影体验并不好。<br>看过旧三国、新三国的观众也不必担心重复，军师联盟中对官渡之战、赤壁之战都是一句话带过，专心讲北方这条故事线。</p>
<p>独播<br>观影的网上渠道，是优酷网独播。也就是除了部分卫视的电视播放权，网络播放权是被优酷网独家买断，只有他家能播，别的家不能播。<br>类似的操作方式，有当年的甄嬛传在乐视网独播。为此，当时乐视网的一位CDN(Content Delivery Network)的技术专家还在InfoQ上做了 如何让100万人同时在线收看《甄嬛传》的技术分享。<br>虽然贾老板最近新闻很多，我当时实在是佩服，独播这个太绝了，老板们有魄力的买断，使视频网站与优质IP互相增强曝光，垄断加速了会员转化，应该是很合算的买卖。</p>
<p>创新<br>新意还体现在，诗经和植入广告。<br>剧中多次出现诗歌，以诗经居多。非常贴合时代背景，因为当时唐诗宋词都没有来得及创作，诗经应该是最大的诗歌类IP，而古代的诗都是歌词，是用来唱的。虽然很遗憾的都失传了，导演还是在古诗演唱上进行了多种尝试，包括曹操在宫里用编钟边敲边唱，还有司马懿家人做饭时用二人转哼唱。诗歌引用也有一个穿帮镜头，曹丕打猎回城，说自己看今天“天朗气清、惠风和畅，正好适合打猎”，引用的是后世王羲之的兰亭集序，曹丕公子在这一刻穿越了。<br>另一个创新是植入广告。作为一名广告从业人员，实在要对导演和优酷点赞，他们在提升用户广告体验上做出了又一次很好的示范。优酷播放本剧的插入广告，都是原班演员出演的古装创意广告，和剧中角色呼应，又界限分明，保证了正片纯净的同时提升了观影体验和商业价值。</p>
<p>演员<br>剧中很多我熟悉的演员。<br>作为吴秀波的粉丝，很高兴看到大器晚成的波叔近年来的人气飙升。心术、黎明之前、离婚律师之后，这是波叔的又一力作。<br>青年司马懿的对手杨修，演员翟天临，很高兴见证他的成长，他可是凭借心术获得了某个最佳新人奖、最佳男配角奖。同科室的两个医生好同事，这次来到了三国，演了一对死对头。第一次演坏人的他个性张扬了很多，演技得到了很好的历练，希望他的戏路越走越宽。<br>由于先入为主的印象，曹操演员于和伟，最早见他演过历史的天空，是个叛徒，虽然后来演过刘备（和这次反过来了），秦始皇，形象越发高大上，但我看他还是总觉得是汉奸。荀彧的演员，王劲松，我最早见他是在北平无战事的军统人员，从对方角度来看算是忍辱负重吧，而且抽很多烟，肺不好，总咳嗽，于是我每次见他总是觉得他肺不好。王劲松近年还参演了琅琊榜，加上这次军师联盟，都是很好的角色，人气和口碑在稳固提升。</p>
<p>文章<br>军师联盟对曹丕进行更丰富的描写，包括他创作《典论》。司马懿还劝过曹丕，如果政治上不成功，比如当不了太子，还有写文章留名这条路。作为演员基本功，李晨也熟读背诵了曹丕的《典论·论文》，一篇讲述文学价值的文章，经典句子有，“盖文章，经国之大业，不朽之盛事。年寿有时而尽，荣乐止乎其身，二者必至之常期，未若文章之无穷。” 其实说的是文章的价值存续期很长，在中国文化中是有深刻共鸣的。<br>曹操除了政治军事历史上的成就，非常令人敬佩的一点是，自己文学成就高，还培养了两个儿子曹丕、曹植文学成就也很高，一家出三个文学家，能与之相提并论的，也只有三苏了。</p>
<p>报道写完了，列两个Action Items吧:</p>
<ul>
<li>看完军师联盟，我现在才看到19集。</li>
<li>有空去趟横店，近距离体验下中国的影视工业。</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/images/qrcode_songzheglobal_2017.jpg" alt="扫描二维码，关注我的微信公众号"></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/junshilianmeng.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;周末，聊个电视剧，就是今天刚刚收官的《军师联盟》，最近热播的三国题材电视剧。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我最早在春节之前看了预告片，就列入今年的看片计划，一直在关注。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;视角&lt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Life" scheme="http://zhesong.info/categories/Life/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Fun" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Fun/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>2016年我读完了14本书</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2016/12/29/book-list-2016/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2016/12/29/book-list-2016/</id>
    <published>2016-12-29T15:50:58.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T09:34:03.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>在今年还剩两周的时候，我过了下三个书单，“读完”，“想读”，“在读”。从“在读”中选出一本，决心把它留在今年。连同这篇读书总结，一起纪念2016。</p>
<p>据谣传，中国人均年阅读量4.35本，日本40本，韩国11本，法国20本，以色列60本。我的表现，今年提升了我国均值外，超过了韩国水平，并向法国、日本看齐。相比2015年我读完的3本书，今年实现了366.7%的爆发式增长。读书类别也从有限的工程协作、散文、量化金融，扩展到全栈工程、科技史、博文集、青春言情小说、科幻、Web开发、成功学、女性护理、白话文言文等丰富领域。他们分别是:</p>
<p>1.《Growth: 全栈增长工程师指南》by 黄峰达，201602<br>这是一本电子书，作者是青年才俊黄峰达。我发现很多技术好，文章好，又声名远播的人，名字都带一个“峰”字，比如阮一峰，廖雪峰，黄峰达。黄峰达同学很年轻，但经验非常丰富，专长于前端，且对全栈工程师颇有心得，写起前端发展史，全栈技术版图，信手拈来，一挥而就。起一个代号Phodal行走江湖，知乎上2万点赞，Github上2万星标，踌躇满志。</p>
<p>2.《硅谷之谜》by 吴军, 201602<br>吴军老师近来写书效率奇高，手上的还没看完，新书又出了。拿到这本书是今年1月林萌大师来加州总部出差，问我要带什么东西。美帝物产丰盈，无所不有，但读中文书不便，就托林萌大师带的这本。拿到手是1月份，扉页还有吴军12月写的序，不足一个月，真是新鲜。读完才知道，原来常路过的Fairchild Avenue，高概率是大名鼎鼎的仙童半导体公司旧址。而硅谷能成为硅谷，真是靠了天时地利人和。临走的时候，把这本书转送给很佩服的一个同事Tech Lead。听说他最近升了Manager，我自己多了一个“靠山”之余，亲眼见证了又一个硅谷华人发迹故事。</p>
<p>3.《MacTalk: 跨越边界》by 池建强, 201602<br>池老师的文章也是越写越好。两年前读他的文章，还觉得微信三剑客道哥、鬼脚七、MacTalk中，数他最水。后来鬼脚七卖2000块一条的围巾并大谈粉丝经济，我这个假粉丝百无聊赖中就取了关；道哥创业成功被阿里回购，俗事愈加繁忙，文章日渐稀少；独剩MacTalk池建强，金枪不倒。说来有些渊源，我读他的第一本文集时，发了条微博，还被他本尊转发，真是荣幸。这本是他的第二本文集，阅读中有很多共鸣之处，比如突然发现自己多少多少岁了，社会家庭要你承担责任了，可内心还觉得自己就是个孩子。</p>
<p>4.《万物生长》by 冯唐，201603<br>偶像冯唐作品。讲的是医学院大学生活，读这种书总能看到自己的影子，有自己做过的、没做过的、想过没做成的、没想过还能那么做的事。做过的再回顾一遍，没做的让小说里的人替我们做。电影一直没看，因为舍不得。</p>
<p>5.《女神一号》by 冯唐，201604<br>生病失声期间读的。生病时无比痛苦，怀念健康的自由。但有个好处，静养时无所事事，正好读书。掐表一算，读完一本没什么难度的不厚的书，8小时上下。据说原型是微博一毛不拔大师，在搜神记系列有一集。这主人公也有赴美留学，回国创业的经历。但很多地方写得很扯淡。</p>
<p>6.《激荡三十年》by 吴晓波，201605<br>读这本书贯穿了我做回国决定的前后。上卷读完是在上海环球金融中心61层谷歌办公室，下卷读完是在拉斯维加斯的机场。在这本书里，我读懂了改革开放。在中国有个好处，我对大部分大公司、大老板的来龙去脉，有个基本了解。因为这些公司历史也不长，从小耳渎目染，读书看报都知道一些，再远的有个洋务运动的底子，也很明了。我一直带着一个问题，就是改革开放以来，回头看，这么多机会，怎么我爸妈、我同学的爸妈，都没能抓住呢，我也采访了我爸妈和大舅(一个体制内的成功人士)。我的总结3点因素吧: 1.大部分人追求安全感，追求铁饭碗、商品粮。2.当时有个背景是大量下乡青年回城无法就业，很多人下海，也是生计所迫，因为没那么多铁饭碗，当时也很受人看不起，后来世事变迁，因祸得福。3.各地套路不同，北方尤其河北主流套路是当公务员、进国企，南方尤其江浙主流套路是做生意，人受自己小环境的影响很大的。顺便提下，今年本来有个机会去参加莆田商会聚餐，火车票都买好了，可惜因故没有去成。</p>
<p>7.《时间移民》by 刘慈欣, 201607<br>雨果奖得主，刘慈欣科幻小说集。时常读读科幻小说，对打开自己想象力有帮助，而且可以帮自己把注意力从很世俗的事上转移开。今年听到一句话总结挺到位的，说人要有宇宙观。如果站在宇宙的大尺度上，自己的那些烦心事，大到人生，大到全人类，在宇宙面前，太渺小了，根本不是个事。</p>
<p>8.《七年就是一辈子》by 李笑来, 201607<br>李笑来是今年中国思想界的很耀眼的一个明星，我还去了一次他在上海国际舞蹈中心的线下讲座，千金一座。他对我的启发很大的，很幸运有这么个人站出来把那些道理讲出来，而且他自己的成功是他的方法论的强有力背书。代表性几个作品，《把时间当做朋友》，《七年就是一辈子》，《得到App:通往财富自由之路》，都不错。好的地方很多，说一个我不喜欢的地方，出现了很多他的“信徒”，搞得像邪教一样。</p>
<p>9.《三十六大》by 冯唐, 201608<br>偶像冯唐作品，散文集。作为4年的GQ订阅用户，冯先生是我刊的专栏作者。好东西不能吃太多，吃多了腻了下次就不想吃了，所以我一直在克制自己，不要短时间读太多冯唐的书。关于冯唐，我有一篇文章，在公众号后台回复“冯唐”。</p>
<p>10.《如何变得有思想》by 阮一峰, 201608<br>阮一峰是我们程序员作家圈的一杆大旗。网上随便搜搜什么技术相关的东西，搜索引擎都能把我们引到阮一峰博客来。作为榜样当然要认真学习，赶快买一本文集来读。</p>
<p>11.《编写高质量代码: 改善Python程序的91个建议》by 张颖 赖勇浩, 201608<br>这本书是借同事的书读的，借来的书果然读的快。说来惭愧，作为一个资深Python助教，很多Python高级语言特性，比如generator, decorator我以前真不知道，因为我学Python的时候书里没有啊，有的特性也没有出世，后来也没用到过，还自以为懂Python的样子。值得一提的是，这不是一本翻译书，而是两位中国作者的原创。</p>
<p>12.《Python Web开发实战》by 董伟明, 201610<br>新书哦。新到买的时候京东自营没有货源，只有第三方商家有。业界公认，Python工程应用只服豆瓣，在这里祝福豆瓣有惊无险。本书作者出自豆瓣，序言也是豆瓣帮集体出动。内容很广，涵盖了Python Web开发后端版图，和我的工作直接相关。这本书出来的正是时候。书出来后作者也就火了，神奇的是作者要沉寂一段时间，不喜欢宁静的生活被打扰。相比出名后的烦恼，没出名的人也都有一点羡慕吧。</p>
<p>13.《女神日常修炼手册》by 余点，201612<br>前些天刚发过文章。长按下方二维码，关注我的微信公众号(songzheglobal)，回复“女神”，可以看到读书笔记。</p>
<p>14.《喻世明言》by 冯梦龙，201612<br>这本算是比较难读的，因为是白话文言文。选它除了因为喜欢，还因为有一个支线设想是写小说，必须有输入。三言二拍是极好的。中国小说，兴于明朝。明代冯梦龙编写的三言，几乎把中国古代有名的故事搜罗殆尽，导致后来凌濛初被书商约稿仿写，很难找到新故事，只好从“奇”上着眼，写得初刻二刻拍案惊奇。临走美国前，我原来那套三言二拍，不忍心捐给Mountain View Public Library被将来1刀1英寸贱卖，在谷歌内搞了个抽签赠书，发了个帖子，公布了抽签源码，效果不错，也算给它找了个好归宿。这书的一个体会是，古代和现代虽然间隔久远，但人性真是一样一样的，那时候的人也想赚钱，“赚些钱钞来使”；也好色，“被他撩拨不过，思那小娘子，定要云雨一番”；也好当官，“从此平步青云，累官至吏部尚书”。确实也有些故事，在今天看来很扯，封建社会三观不同，可以理解。</p>
<p>任务完成得不错，写完这12篇文章，读完这14本书，正好就过完了这16年。</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;在今年还剩两周的时候，我过了下三个书单，“读完”，“想读”，“在读”。从“在读”中选出一本，决心把它留在今年。连同这篇读书总结，一起纪念2016。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;据谣传，中国人均年阅读量4.35本，日本40本，韩国11本，法国20本，以色列60本。我的表现，今年提升了我国均
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Life" scheme="http://zhesong.info/categories/Life/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Reading" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Reading/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>有一本书叫《女神日常修炼手册》</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2016/12/21/way-to-be-goddess/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2016/12/21/way-to-be-goddess/</id>
    <published>2016-12-21T08:52:40.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T08:32:01.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>最近读完了一本神书，还真是“神”书，《女神日常修炼手册》，和大家分享下。</p>
<p>作为一个男士，其实我更想读的书是《男神日常修炼手册》，可惜并没有，只好先读《女神日常修炼手册》，想来道理也是相通的。生活中，我们都见过很多很完美的人，展示给我们光鲜亮丽的一面。他们和我们相遇时，已经达到了一个很好的境界。但没有人生来完美，他们现在的好，是过去很多年积累下来的，这中间的过程，更值得我们借鉴。<br>我的一个私心是对当前网红经济的调研。对一个技术人来说，在这个网红经济与超级IP的时代，一个很好的范式是和网红合作，成为她的CTO与生意伙伴，而网红则是女神的一种初级形态。另一个私心则是为了自己的幸福，作为一个仍然没有放弃爱情理想和女神幻想的人，我需要知道女神们最青睐哪种男生，哪种女生具有潜质成为未来的女神，就到这本书里去找找答案。</p>
<p>日常<br>关键词是精致，对自己的不妥协，一种不精致毋宁死的态度。<br>第一件事，就是瘦下去，不二法门是少吃多运动。节食这件事可能没有那么痛苦。作者先抛出了一个场景，微博某女星深夜发了一张火锅图，很多微观群众就展开想象了，有的认为，她只是发图根本就没吃，不然保持不了那样的身材；有的认为，她一定很痛苦，吃不了肚子里咕咕叫，还要强颜欢笑拍照。作者说，更大的可能，她吃了而且大快朵颐，或者只吃了一点点，但很尽兴。我读到这里是费解的，怎么可能？再往下读就明白了。首先如果一个人少食或者吃素，初期可能会痛苦，坚持一段时间，体质和胃口就会适应，所以吃一点就会饱，见到了肉也没有很想吃的欲望。而且很多人平时坚持健康的饮食和规律的锻炼，完成任务后，偶尔会给自己一次放纵的机会，吃完这顿大餐，明天恢复计划。<br>关于护肤这件事，我印象很深的是，作者把皮肤比作人体的排泄器官，所以关键就不是涂什么抹什么的问题了，而是如何保持它的畅通，和从源头上清除垃圾。护理上，就是保持清洁，定期补水，多喝水加补水面膜。调理上，则是早睡多运动吃清淡。吃上还是有很多可做的，上班族外卖吃多了，容易长成外卖脸，因为外卖食品往往重油厚味不卫生。如果午餐不可避免吃外卖，至少早餐可以改善。在作者的启发下，我已经连续两周坚持自制早餐，一碗红枣小米粥加两个煮鸡蛋，被同学戏称为月子餐。</p>
<p>心法<br>关键词是优雅。优雅的体现是一丝不苟的细节与不着急的心态，优雅的来源是真正的自信与高贵的内心，优雅的塑成是良好的教养与长期的修炼。按我的理解，从美女进阶为女神，是要有仙气的，就是超脱于常人的地方。比如人性两大弱点，贪婪与恐惧，离这两点越远，就离神更近。<br>更具有操作性的建议，有享受孤独，多读书，多旅行，甚至独自旅行。因为人提高自己三个途径嘛，读万卷书，行万里路，阅人无数。还有要杜绝坏情绪，因为坏情绪对人的健康和容貌有直接影响。<br>书中还有几篇文章写给被逼婚的“剩女”，恋爱中的“痴女”的，纠结中的“怨女”的，很有借鉴意义。</p>
<p>匹配<br>那女神般的女生，都嫁给什么样的男生呢？我心里的答案是暖男。<br>作者给出的答案，出乎我的意料，因为三观太正了，只提了五点: 人品好，重情义，正能量，幽默感，上进心。<br>想一想也是有道理的。能写出这么一本书的女生，必定古灵精怪如黄蓉一般，自然偏爱郭靖型的，宁可笨一点好驾驭，人品要好。重情义也包括顾家，因为女性的刚需是陪伴。正能量要做到天不怕地不怕，无比自信，像一个男人的样子。幽默经常被提到。上进心的高级形态是情怀。其实在这个逐利冷漠的年代，能做到这五点，很难得的。</p>
<p>采访<br>后面的篇幅作者采访了很多心中的“女神”，有儿时玩伴，国际名模，选美冠军，知名演员，人气网红等等，类型各有不同。想来作者能培养出自己的女神气质，和能接触到很优秀的同伴有关系。虽然难免比较，但身边都是很优秀的人，自己会变得更好。<br>这些人套路不同，我找到的相同点是，她们都很有追求，且敢于有不一样的想法。比如留学生学霸有一段艰辛的实习生涯，不觉得苦难，而为终于从事到梦想中的工作而幸福；比如宁可又老又丑又普通，也不愿又老又丑又成功；比如一个海外代购不满足于小本生意，决心开创自己的品牌；比如要在贵圈中保持文艺气质，区别于那些妖艳贱货。</p>
<p>俗话说，取法乎上得其中，取法乎中得其下。真正地女神，很难炼成，而这本书的火爆，代表了大家向往美好事物，美好生活的愿望。虽然生活艰难，我仍然相信这是个好的时代，好到每个人都有机会成为自己想成为的人。<br>祝你心想事成。</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;最近读完了一本神书，还真是“神”书，《女神日常修炼手册》，和大家分享下。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;作为一个男士，其实我更想读的书是《男神日常修炼手册》，可惜并没有，只好先读《女神日常修炼手册》，想来道理也是相通的。生活中，我们都见过很多很完美的人，展示给我们光鲜亮丽的一面。他们和我们
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>新闻会客厅·宋哲回国了(下)</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2016/10/08/back-to-china-ii/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2016/10/08/back-to-china-ii/</id>
    <published>2016-10-08T03:25:09.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T08:32:01.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>在十一长假的第7天，我们新闻会客厅再次邀请到了宋哲先生，继续聊聊他回国后的生活。</p>
<p>友情提示：这次访谈是上期节目的一个后续，上期节目请点击链接<a href="2016/09/01/back-to-china/">新闻会客厅·宋哲回国了(上)</a>。</p>
<p>Q: 主持人 宋哲<br>A: 特邀嘉宾 宋哲</p>
<p>Q: 宋先生，晚上好。<br>A: 主持人，你好。</p>
<p>Q: 距离上次访谈转眼已经过去一个月了，还经历了两个中国特色的假期。假期怎么过的呀？有没有去游历祖国大好河山。<br>A: 假期过的还不错。中秋节回了趟家，和爸妈一起过节。<br>Q: 哇，这是这些年第一次回家过中秋节吗？<br>A: 倒不是，去年中秋也是回国在家里过的，还因为签证被审查，在家多滞留了一段时间，也是因祸得福。今年中秋节因为是临时决定，从上海到北京再辗转回家，到家都凌晨两点了。热了两碗粥，吃了半块月饼，和爸妈说说笑笑，就是今年的中秋夜了。<br>Q: 你这虽然晚了点，但中秋夜能到家，还真是幸福。那国庆节呢？有没有出去玩？<br>A: 国庆期间我都在上海，见见朋友，在上海四处逛逛。去浦东车展看豪车和美女，在迪士尼小镇欣赏百老汇歌剧狮子王，在外滩和武警们一起看看游客和江景，在田子坊听苏州评弹未遂改成了听相声。<br>Q: 哟，你对评弹还有兴趣啊？<br>A: 对呀。不知道你有没有印象，老上海标志性的那种美女图，贴在大街上，印在烟盒上。就是，一个美女，一点点胖，留个短发或者盘起来，穿着旗袍，坐姿，微笑，手里抱着一个琵琶。那就是评弹。<br>Q: 哦~有印象，有印象。而且咿咿呀呀的也挺好听的。<br>A: 对的，好看也好听。张艺谋《金陵十三钗》里面，那个“我有一段情，唱给诸公听”，就是评弹，那声音我记了5年，一直到今天。<br>Q: 那个啊，我知道，是有名的评弹《无锡景》。好说啊，有机会带你去苏州听评弹，高铁只要半个小时。正好我们台里对您这样的嘉宾，是有公关经费的。<br>A: 哈哈，你们台给力啊，以后我常来录节目，去了苏州我请你吃饭。</p>
<p>Q: 这个可以有。我这里还有上次没问完的问题哈，咱们继续。回国也有4个月了吧，怎么样，各方面都适应吗？<br>A: 还行，都挺适应的，吃住都还习惯。<br>Q: 会想美国吗？<br>A: 有时候会的。尤其是在街上见到奥迪的时候，跑步到外滩见到环球金融中心的时候，一想，本来这都是我的东西呀。可能和曹雪芹写书的时候回忆自己的日常有点像吧，也有点像在朋友圈看到美美的前女友的照片。<br>Q: 哈哈，还能这么类比啊。<br>A: 嗯。有时候点了外卖总觉得卫生不放心，也会想美国，谷歌的饭虽然不好吃，但卫生肯定有保障而且是有机食品。对了，还有发工资的时候。<br>Q: 理解。毕竟大幅降薪，不是每个人都能接受的，很多人也从来没经历过。这一点我还挺佩服你的。怎么样，后悔吗？<br>A: 不后悔。这些事情都是来之前预料到的，而且很多事就是有代价的。想清楚了就决定，决定了就做，做了就不后悔，要坚持。</p>
<p>Q: 说得好。你当时做决定的时候爸妈支持吗？<br>A: 最开始的时候是反对的，还电话回复了我三点意见: 1.在原公司继续积累，提升能力; 2.在美国多攒钱; 3.赶快随便找个女朋友，“我们”很着急。<br>我当时听了很生气，直接口头回复了我的三点反馈: 1.如果说提升能力的话，小一点的更早期的公司更锻炼人; 2.攒钱这件事吧，其实职业生涯中大部分收入在中后期，早期以个人成长为主; 3.关于第三点这完全就是错的嘛。<br>后来4月份我们在北京见面，充分沟通下，爸妈也是理解支持的，心里是因为我能回来而高兴。<br>在之后5月9日，在我为搬家的事而发愁的时候，我爸发来了一条微信: “这些年总的安排和做法，在大的目标和方向上都是正确的。下步排好诸项落实的轻重缓急，注意节奏，避免长途奔袭和劳顿，休息好，精力才能够用，启程前半月把所有事情处理妥为好，留出心静时段，也便于对过往经历、人文环境等，梳理自身经验，搞好小结，到时轻松履新。”<br>Q: 哇，你爸这水平很高啊，是做领导的吧。<br>A: 嗯。看到这短信我还蛮感动的。第一句算是帮我定了性，有点像90年代初大家对是否走市场经济道路总是争论，摇摆不定，邓小平爷爷南巡一番讲话，发展才是硬道理，大家心就定了，继续搞建设。最后一句，“轻松履新”四个字，我是回味良久，越念越轻松。</p>
<p>Q: 赞。我知道你做回中国人，肯定会有很多新奇的想法，可以分享一下吗？<br>A: 可以的。其实我心里面一直有个写小说的想法，这个东西比钱和权更有价值，也很有成就感和乐趣。说难也不难，先有一个背景框架和故事主线，规划好了，往里填东西就行。说简单也不简单，因为问题是怎么填东西。必要的写作练习是肯定的，更必要的是人生的阅历。<br>比如，南京曹雪芹少年时对奢侈品的痴迷，北京张海鹏的多维度广空间跨界人生，海宁查良镛在抗日时期的流亡求学生活，天津张牧野十年文革的经历和听老人们讲的故事，都对他们日后写出好作品有帮助。而我如果一直留在硅谷写代码，那我的2017将和2016，2015，2014，其实区别不大。也有一种流行的说法是，你究竟是过了100天，还是只过了1天，重复100遍。我选择前者。<br>这也是我选择上海的一个原因。这里是东方小巴黎，冒险家的乐园。众多民国思想家、艺术家、政要乃至流氓大亨，都曾在这里生活。我所居住的，就是当年法租界的核心区域。躲雨时，转身一看是巡捕房旧址；早上跑步，可以路过孙中山故居；吃完饭散步，发现我家和周公馆是邻居；感觉自己生活在历史里。偶像之一杜月笙先生曾在这里打拼。而今天的淮海路新天地，俨然成为了上海的时尚中心，很潮。很多文学影视作品，主人公都有一段上海滩经历。我选择来上海，也是对我人生阅历的一个丰富。<br>Q: 有道理，期待你的作品啊，你这部小说肯定好看。<br>A: 谢谢，30岁写本小说可能差不多。也许到时想法变了，改说相声了呢。<br>Q: 哈哈哈，看你看你。</p>
<p>Q: 说说公司吧，小红书现在状态怎么样？<br>A: 状态蛮好的，大环境小环境都很好。我在里面，很多次感受到，这件正在发生的事，还真是对啊。就是说，很多好的事情在发生，而他们都是我认为他可以成事的征兆。有机会我们可以线下聊，在节目里就不多说了，以免有植入广告的嫌疑。有兴趣加入的朋友请直接找我内推。<br>Q: 好的。那有什么可以分享的随便说说吧？<br>A: 可以。比如说，我们公司有很多牛人。国内优秀工程师的技术水平，其实是完全不输美国的。我观察我身边很多很厉害的人，具有两个特点，一个是对自己做的事真的有兴趣，以致于外人看是加班加点很辛苦，其实是他喜欢做这件事，一直做，根本停不下来；还有一个特点是被需求倒逼，和公司一起成长，年纪轻轻被逼成了技术专家，之后每天各种人来找他请教问题，解决问题，真是让人羡慕。<br>公司员工之优秀也是我始料未及的，可以用人才辈出来形容。海归工程师中，几乎集齐了硅谷一线公司，比如Google, Facebook, Linkedin, Microsoft, Twitter, Airbnb, Uber等等；很多高管有哈佛斯坦福MBA，新入职员工中也不乏普林斯顿、斯坦福本科；市场行销人员有宝洁金牌销售，麦肯锡战略顾问，对冲基金经理；时尚社区运营部还有一线时尚杂志主编。除了业务过硬，才艺丰富，大家还都是很有品质会生活的人，朋友圈中不过节时，大家晒晒宠物、喝喝咖啡、写写微信公众号文章，过节时很多人出国旅行，在全世界遇到你。<br>Q: 听起来很赞啊，我都想去投一份简历，和你们一起工作。<br>A: 欢迎欢迎。</p>
<p>Q: 好的，今天的节目就到这里。再次欢迎你回国，祝你一切顺利！<br>A: 谢谢祝福！</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;在十一长假的第7天，我们新闻会客厅再次邀请到了宋哲先生，继续聊聊他回国后的生活。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;友情提示：这次访谈是上期节目的一个后续，上期节目请点击链接&lt;a href=&quot;2016/09/01/back-to-china/&quot;&gt;新闻会客厅·宋哲回国了(上)&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;

    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Life" scheme="http://zhesong.info/categories/Life/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Interview" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Interview/"/>
    
      <category term="Chinese" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Chinese/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>新闻会客厅·宋哲回国了(上)</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2016/09/01/back-to-china/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2016/09/01/back-to-china/</id>
    <published>2016-09-01T03:50:05.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T08:32:01.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>9月1日是个好日子，我们又要开学了。今天非常高兴，邀请到了老朋友宋哲，来到我们新闻会客厅，聊一聊他回国后的新生活。</p>
<p>下面是访谈实录。</p>
<p>Q：主持人 宋哲<br>A：特邀嘉宾 宋哲</p>
<p>Q：宋先生好！欢迎来到新闻会客厅。<br>A：主持人你好。</p>
<p>Q：哎呀，请你出来做节目还真是不容易，我们前后联系过你很多次，这下终于约出来了。<br>A：谢谢你们的关心哈。毕竟是比较大的改变，我给自己定了3个月的静默期，好让自己安心过度。现在3个月快过去了，又赶上9月1日开学日，正好公布一下消息，告别一下过去，正式开始新阶段。<br>Q：啊，理解的。大家知道了肯定会有大量的询问，尤其是像你这样朋友多的，散伙饭就要吃无数顿吧。<br>A：是的。所以这次变动保持了最大程度的低调，只通知了最小范围的人。所以还是要借这个机会，向湾区的很多朋友说声抱歉，原谅我的不告而别。<br>Q: 不过说实在的，你这保密工作做得也够牛的，从外面完全看不出来啊，而且一点风声都没有。</p>
<p>A：哈哈，谢谢夸奖。我先简单介绍一下吧，我回国了，离开硅谷，从谷歌离职，来到上海加入了一家C轮的创业公司。<br>Q：还真是蛮意外的。那怎么想的呢？美国不是挺好的么，怎么就回来了呢？<br>A：怎么说呢，各种原因吧。<br>其实，在过去的两年，有两个问题一直在我心中挥之不去：回不回国？创不创业？而且，从来没有过一个明确的很好的解答，也不会有这样的标准答案。<br>去年2015年8月份罗辑思维的罗振宇，来到硅谷索菲亚大学，协同伴米网有一场活动，我和超过500位他的硅谷粉丝们，一起听了那次演讲。罗胖开场不久，就不问而答了这个问题，大意是，“如果你想创业，或者说抓住机遇，做一番事业，那要去中国；如果你的追求是一个好的生活，那在美国好好待着其实挺好的。” 我当时感觉，罗胖这话说是说了，可其实也相当于啥都没说，把现场的人都照顾到了，你怎么着都行。<br>今年2016年3月份，我接待中科大新创校友会秘书长刘志峰，先是晚上十点出发去San Jose一个校友家里和他会面，也提出了我心中的这个长久困惑。他回答的大意是，“中国和美国，其实在哪边发展都很好。其实你们现在啥都没有，也不拉家带口，怎么着都行啊，有合适的机会，说回就回了，可能也挺好。”<br>我也将这两个问题和一些我很佩服的、在中美都工作过的同事们讲过，有的反馈是，“首先中国生活品质不如美国。另外从职业生涯来讲，最好能在谷歌做到Level 6再说，这样个人的能力和市场价值能提升到一个很好的水平。” 也有的反馈是，“既然宋哲同学有这种向往，那可以去经历一下。哪怕不行，再回来呗，这样你的心就定了。”</p>
<p>Q：那还真是众说纷纭。说说你个人的想法呢。<br>A：我其实从来不是坚定的留美派，一直接纳回国的可能性，甚至很向往一个中国人的生活，和在祖国发展更多的可能性。网上也有很多经典文章，对比一个硅谷小伙和一个北京小伙，主流意见多认为，硅谷小伙多金但无聊，北京小伙快乐但压力更大，而双方在互相羡慕。</p>
<p>我很向往的国内的一个好处，是作为一个native speaker和native resident的巨大优势。首先在沟通上可以实现100%表达和接收，心理上有主流文化的认同感，行为上没有移民政策的约束具有更大的自由度。而在国外，幼功扎实、受过高等教育的我们说着英语简单句和简单词，变成了当地没有文化的人；对美国事，我们有一种我是外国人的超脱心态，对中国事，则有一种隔岸观火的漠然心态，总是不自觉地置身在一个拧巴的边缘地带；行为上的有形无形约束，例如工作签证是不能开Uber的，只能从事和专业相关的工作，无工作状态不能超过3个月，还有太多被限制了的可能性。</p>
<p>还有值得一提的是，旧金山湾区恶劣的约会生态，这一点也是大家所公认的。其实相比早期移民，我们还算幸福的。我读《美国种族简史》，当年的很多旧金山华人矿工，那些不能从广东福建老家搬运的，要无奈地和当地非洲裔女性组成家庭。<br>在海外即使组成家庭后，还要面对文化代沟。我见过很多例子，诸如在饭店吃饭，母亲对儿子讲中文，儿子回的每一句都是英文，背后的原因是学校里小孩子们都说Chinese is not cool。去年谷歌公司组织一年一度Great America游乐场游玩日，我在水上乐园边上躺着晒太阳，不远处一个同事带着女儿和爸妈来，爷爷奶奶和孙女完全无法交流，要靠猜。<br>第二代、第三代移民，都可以过得很好，而第一代移民则付出了最大的代价，对下失去了很多乐趣，对上则对父母亏欠太多。</p>
<p>Q：让爸妈一大把年纪学英语，还真是很残酷啊。<br>A：闲扯一句，有时候我还挺羡慕有的同学爸妈是大学老师，或者英语很好，来了美国他们爸妈自己说着英语就到处玩了，特省心。</p>
<p>Q：哈哈，那还挺好玩的。我还有个问题，为什么不回谷歌中国呢？<br>A：恩，当时也是一个选择。我主要的考虑是个人的成长，和对新公司的兴趣。<br>其实这两年还有一个问题一直困惑着我。国内对回国的硅谷工程师的期望，常常是一个专家型人才，比如说这个人精通机器学习个性化推荐，是个蓝牙模块专家，或者有多少多少专利。可大型互联网公司的工程师，分工更细致，项目格局小周期短，应用的也是现成的工具和平台，并没有技术上很深刻的挑战和积累，这种模式下螺丝钉们很难成长为专家。而高速发展的公司里，个人可以承担起更大的责任，快速增长的需求会倒逼技术革新，工程师也随之一起成长。对于有志于全栈工程师的同学，小公司也有更多的机会把人锻炼成多面手。</p>
<p>关于老东家，说句玩笑话哈，其实开始的时候，我要离开了就开始想，这公司什么时候走下坡路啊，这样不就证明我走对了么。但稍微一想不对，谷歌公司还有着强劲的增长动力，市值一度世界第一，全球科技创新的排头兵，技术积累雄厚，产业链完整，在人工智能、虚拟现实等新领域占据优势，在相当长一段时间内仍将保持上升势头。实在是幸运，这是我的第一份全职工作，学到很多，也认识很多牛人。</p>
<p>Q：说完了老东家，那谈谈你的新公司呗。<br>A：新公司名叫小红书。<br>Q：啊，原来是小红书！我知道，很多妹子都在用，我们公司前台也经常收到他们的红盒子包裹。不过我一个男的倒是没用过。<br>A：那你也下载装一个呗，里面有很多好东西和大家的分享。我不时也会发一下优惠券到朋友圈。<br>Q：好嘞，这就下。那讲讲你的求职经历呗？<br>A：好。今年2月29日，四年才有的这么一天，小红书来硅谷计算机历史博物馆(Computer History Museum)宣讲。其实我去之前并没有跳槽打算，只是想去看看Tiger，小红书的CTO，也是前Google上海站site director，是谷歌华人中排名前三的大牛，想亲眼看一看。<br>听了CEO Charlwin和Tiger的宣讲，当时就感觉很心动，一个是因为消费升级这事我信，这是我年初听罗辑思维才知道的新概念。在收入提高、物质丰富后，中国经济必然要经历消费升级，人们由追求性价比转为追求品质，在国内商品愈趋同质化、大打价格战的今天，海外商品成为品质好物的重要渠道。另一个心动的原因是，工程师团队只有40人。<br>于是那场活动中，我在台上和台下各问了两个问题加深个人印象，回去思考了一天后隔天开始联系面试。中途3月份因为降温感冒，整夜咳嗽之后一度失声一周，想来也是好事多磨。后来4月份回北京参加QCon，特意绕道上海，来公司实地考察，最终确定。</p>
<p>（待续）</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;9月1日是个好日子，我们又要开学了。今天非常高兴，邀请到了老朋友宋哲，来到我们新闻会客厅，聊一聊他回国后的新生活。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;下面是访谈实录。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q：主持人 宋哲&lt;br&gt;A：特邀嘉宾 宋哲&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q：宋先生好！欢迎来到新闻会客厅。&lt;br&gt;A：主持人你
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Life" scheme="http://zhesong.info/categories/Life/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Interview" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Interview/"/>
    
      <category term="Chinese" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Chinese/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Product Views Behind WeChat</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2016/04/13/product-views-behind-wechat-en/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2016/04/13/product-views-behind-wechat-en/</id>
    <published>2016-04-13T06:28:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T08:32:01.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>《Product Views Behind WeChat》 is written by Xiaolong (Allen) Zhang, the founding father of WeChat. The work came from a special internal talk in Tencent on July 24, 2012. The original talk was 8 hours and 20 minutes long with a 180+ pages PPT. Excluding the confidential part, a 139-page PPT was published.<br>I wrote this article to summarize the PPT to one article, and translated to English for the world.<br>You can find link to Chinese version at bottom. </p>
<p>p1: Product Views Behind WeChat<br>Original Author: Xiaolong (Allen) Zhang</p>
<p>p2:</p>
<ul>
<li>Review of WeChat</li>
<li>Chapter of User</li>
<li>Chapter of Need</li>
<li>Chapter of Design</li>
<li>Chapter of Quality</li>
<li>Chapter of UI</li>
</ul>
<p>p3: Review of WeChat</p>
<ul>
<li>433 days, 100 million users</li>
<li>New entrance to mobile internet</li>
</ul>
<p>p4:<br>Kickoff<br>(Nov 19, 2010)<br>Users reaches 100 million<br>1.0 Jan 26<br>2.0 May 10 voice talkback<br>2.5 Aug 3 check nearby users<br>3.0 Oct 1, shaking, floating bottle<br>3.5 Dec 20, QR Code<br>4.0 Apr 19, friend zone, open interface<br>4.2 July 19, voice chat, video chat</p>
<p>p5: Product Managers sit by the God</p>
<ul>
<li>They know humanity.</li>
<li>They Know psychology of the mass.</li>
<li>Product Managers are like the God. They build system, make rules, and let the mass evolve in the system.</li>
</ul>
<p>p6: Know the reactor of the environment</p>
<ul>
<li>My experiment: the difference between making weibo (Chinese twitter) posts on the go and on desktop: desktop screen(weibo post iteself, content) is also environment.</li>
<li>The people you followed in weibo is your world.</li>
<li>The difference between photo taking in friend zone and Qzone album.</li>
<li>Product builds the environment and determines user reaction.  </li>
</ul>
<p>p7: People are lazy</p>
<ul>
<li>Laziness results in invention.</li>
<li>Lazyness powers innovation.</li>
<li>Case: voice search contacts.</li>
</ul>
<p>p8: Fasion is the drive.</p>
<ul>
<li>“Because everyone else is using it.”</li>
<li>People follow.</li>
<li>For internet products, fashion is a key drive.</li>
<li>Don’t over-instrumentalize.</li>
</ul>
<p>p9: People are impatient</p>
<ul>
<li>Users are not patient enough to read your instructions.</li>
<li>If you can’t make user fall in love with you in one minute…</li>
<li>Don’t grab users to use you product if your product is not good enough yet.</li>
</ul>
<p>p10: People don’t like studying.</p>
<ul>
<li>The sunset of blog. RSS?</li>
<li>Toilet principle: don’t feed long content that user can’t read through on toilet.</li>
</ul>
<p>p11: People are a crowd</p>
<ul>
<li>The crowd : a study of the popular mind</li>
<li>Crowd IQ is below individual IQ.</li>
<li>Internet products face the crow rather than individuals.</li>
<li>Don’t treat the crowd in the way you treat individuals, especially in internet products.</li>
</ul>
<p>p12: Value diaosi grassroot users</p>
<ul>
<li>#Thinking Everyday# facebook, pinterest, instagram, path etc. solve the problem of existence feeling. Existence feeling is that people feel lost and undervalued when they detach from SNS. Such products can’t be popular in China, because Chinese face another problem which is at a lower level than existence feeling which is the living feeling. But the diaosi grassroot group in China have pressure of living, and also long for existence feeling. To understand the mainstream user feelings and needs, we need to start from diaosi grassroot users.</li>
</ul>
<p>p13: Find the essance from everyday experience.</p>
<ul>
<li>Galaxy Note: Fashion? Easier for long-nail users to type.</li>
<li>Touchable switch is closer to human than traditional switch.</li>
<li>Great products should satisfy emotional needs. </li>
</ul>
<p>p14: Let non-weibo users to use your product</p>
<ul>
<li>They are the mainstream users who are too lazy to use weibo.</li>
<li>They are around you.</li>
<li>Keep it in mind, they are your users.</li>
</ul>
<p>p15: Humanization is emphathy.</p>
<ul>
<li>You can’t understand others, but you can understand yourself.</li>
<li>You need to understand common psychologies of human. </li>
</ul>
<p>p16: Need is to satisfy people’s greed, anger and madness.</p>
<ul>
<li>The ultimate goal of products is to satisfy humanity needs.</li>
<li>Don’t add your moral sense to products.</li>
<li>Satisfy greed, anger and madness, but also ask users to send fewer wechat messages. It is a ridiculous world.</li>
<li>“Product is a combination of technology and art.” Steve Jobs.</li>
</ul>
<p>p17: New ideas are 99% wrong.</p>
<ul>
<li>Most “I have a good idea” cases are way far from the needs.</li>
<li>Don’t imagine needs.</li>
</ul>
<p>p18: Don’t build whatever user asks.</p>
<ul>
<li>Don’t satisfy their needs directly.</li>
<li>User needs are scattered. Solution is to abstract them.</li>
<li>User feedbacks can only help you learn about their thoughts.</li>
</ul>
<p>p19: Most new functions can be cut off.</p>
<ul>
<li>Think it back, how many features did you build which turns to be unnecessary.</li>
</ul>
<p>p20: Don’t find needs from peer products.</p>
<ul>
<li>Is doodle important?</li>
<li>You can’t understand needs deeply from peer products.</li>
</ul>
<p>p21: Don’t listen to needs from PM.</p>
<ul>
<li>They are not users but think they represent users.</li>
<li>Their analysis are too rational.</li>
<li>They will ask you to add features like, online or not, sent to phone or not, read or not, grouping, photo filter, doodle, sync across multi-platforms, save messages on cloud, send text, picture and video together to timeline, multi-avatars, like on avatars, PC version, auto-import friends from contacts, group name card, and so on … “Please go and use other products.”</li>
</ul>
<p>p22: Needs come from your understanding of users.</p>
<ul>
<li>Needs are not from survey.</li>
<li>Needs are not from analysis.</li>
<li>Needs are not from discussion.</li>
<li>Needs are not from competitors.</li>
</ul>
<p>p23: Feel the users trends from weibo</p>
<ul>
<li>Spend 1 hour daily on wechat to see how they use your products.</li>
<li>Their scenarios, feelings, etc.</li>
<li>What is the time trends of their era?</li>
<li>Ignore opinions from critics.</li>
<li>Wait for them to say “it was fun!”</li>
</ul>
<p>p24: Get insights from user discussions</p>
<ul>
<li>The weibo posts are reactions from real scenarios.</li>
<li>Case: Stone, scissors, cloth.</li>
<li>Nothing can stop human from playing stone, scissors and cloth on wechat voice chat.</li>
</ul>
<p>p25: Each epoch has its own product.</p>
<ul>
<li>Keep sharp on time trends</li>
<li>From QQ to WeChat.</li>
</ul>
<p>p26: Satisfy your own needs by satisfying user needs</p>
<ul>
<li>You can’t truly understand others.</li>
<li>You can’t satisfy massive individual needs.</li>
<li>Most people think in the same way. Capture the real massive needs from yourself.</li>
<li>Case: read.</li>
<li>Case: voice to input reminder, voice search on people.</li>
</ul>
<p>p27: Find the psychological appeals behind needs</p>
<ul>
<li>Needs can be summarized as psychological appeals.</li>
<li>Floating bottles: satisfy the appeal to speak and curiosity. It’s a great example of psychological drive. People have such a strong desire to tell, even as competitive as mail.</li>
<li>If we build floating bottle just for social, we won’t get the essence. (Case: send floating bottles or text?)  </li>
</ul>
<p>p28: The drive of psychological satisfaction is way better than tools, even better than saving money.</p>
<ul>
<li>An alternative money-saving text tool won’t succeed. We would be in trouble if we target at a money-saving tool.</li>
<li>WeChat is not QQ. “WeChat is a life style”.</li>
<li>WeChat is a life style. It reflects the priority of psychological satisfaction.</li>
</ul>
<p>p29: “Cool” wins over features.</p>
<ul>
<li>Cool! (Goal of marketing is to make users feel cool.)</li>
<li>It was fun! (You get it if weibo posts say it was fun.)</li>
<li>Cool is the foundation for word-of-mouth broadcasting.</li>
<li>Cool is the experience. Experience is easier than feature to be broadcasted.</li>
</ul>
<p>p30: Build for the mass effect: nearby people</p>
<ul>
<li>Case: nearby people.</li>
<li>If it’s not for stranger social, it’s for curiosity.</li>
<li>What will happen?</li>
<li>It has the social effects. Everyone is observing and observed in the meanwhile.</li>
<li>For the first time, they saw each other in real life.</li>
</ul>
<p>p31: Build for the mass effect: shaking</p>
<ul>
<li>People like simple actions.</li>
<li>People are curious of randomness.</li>
<li>People are curious of peers from diversified spaces.</li>
<li>It has mass effect.</li>
</ul>
<p>p32: Build for the idea: friend zone</p>
<ul>
<li>Idea: People need to gain existence feeling from attention of friends. Photo is the perfect medium for interactions. People just need 3 or 5 friends. People don’t want to expose their friends, but want to be in a crowd.</li>
<li>A more private community than facebook and path.</li>
<li>Build it because you want to use it yourself. </li>
</ul>
<p>p33: Focus on main scenario, don’t build complete features.</p>
<ul>
<li>It’s easy to build to be big and complete, but hard to build less.</li>
<li>If you don’t have the ability to simplify complexities, control your desire to build more.</li>
<li>Building more comes from your inconfidence.</li>
<li>The coolness of finding some needs each day is much more rewarding than proposing some needs.</li>
<li>Case: friend zone only allows photo posts. Writing 140 characters is much harder than a photo.</li>
</ul>
<p>p34: Don’t reversly infer needs from strategy analysis</p>
<ul>
<li>Microsoft, Nokia, Google</li>
</ul>
<p>p35: It’s a lie that we get needs from survey.</p>
<ul>
<li>The needs got from mass surveys are not true. (For the need of a group, users will tell you that they want QQ group.)</li>
<li>User feedbacks help improve experiences. But they won’t tell you anything new to build.</li>
<li>The needs from stats are even a lie.</li>
</ul>
<p>p36: Needs are from the curiosity to mass effect.</p>
<ul>
<li>Floating bottle</li>
<li>Nearby people</li>
<li>Shaking</li>
</ul>
<p>p37: Needs are from self needs and nearby friend feedbacks</p>
<ul>
<li>Bluetooth</li>
<li>Web WeChat</li>
<li>TODO on top.</li>
<li>Migration when switching phones.</li>
</ul>
<p>p38: Needs are from understanding of current life trends</p>
<ul>
<li>Friend zone: People need to gain existence feeling from interactions with friends safely, and feel comfortable.</li>
</ul>
<p>p39: Needs are from understanding of platforms</p>
<ul>
<li>Open platform interface is beautiful</li>
<li>Open platform ecosystem is alluring</li>
<li>Open platform brings the uncertainty worth to wait.</li>
<li>Ecosystem instead of individual products</li>
</ul>
<p>p40: Needs are from understanding of information flow</p>
<ul>
<li>Subscription platform: make all messages pushable</li>
<li>Every individual can be outstanding</li>
<li>Broadcast brands via friends.</li>
</ul>
<p>p41:<br><img src="/images/wechat_p41.png" alt=""></p>
<p>p42: Needs are from building new system</p>
<ul>
<li>Popularize QR code so it becomes the entrance.</li>
<li>Satisfy crowd’s psychological or economical needs by building simple rules and self-sustained system.</li>
</ul>
<p>p43: Determine new version features by last minute</p>
<ul>
<li>Don’t pre-plan features for new versions. Determine features of next version when current version is finished.</li>
<li>Plan in mind about all possible features.</li>
<li>Important features will come up to you at the right time.</li>
<li>Case: nearby people.</li>
</ul>
<p>p44: World is new</p>
<ul>
<li>Forget old data and even experience.</li>
<li>Be sharp on current and future trends.</li>
<li>PC’s entrance is search box, mobile entrance is QR code. </li>
</ul>
<p>p45: We get products by its evolvement, rather than plan.</p>
<ul>
<li>The TODOs of each WeChat version were determined only after the last version was published.</li>
<li>It’s impossible to know what the product is like in next half year. Planning is a lie.</li>
<li>It’s better to determine product version later, and do it based on current users and judgement on the current environment.</li>
</ul>
<p>p46: The products with DNA will evolve.</p>
<ul>
<li>DNA is the values and insights of a product.</li>
<li>If we view product as a living object, it has its DNA.</li>
</ul>
<p>p47: Mass effect is the core of social products</p>
<ul>
<li>By knowing inner human desires, build virtual society rules, trigger mass effect, and let the mass push the rules to evolve.</li>
<li>Case: how to play with celebrities? </li>
</ul>
<p>p48: It is not right to put users to low, middle and high brackets.</p>
<ul>
<li>Build products that everyone loves.</li>
<li>It’s not professional to build generic products in a young-age way.</li>
<li>People are equal in front of products.<br><img src="/images/wechat_p48.png" alt=""></li>
</ul>
<p>p49: Build product structure first, then functional details.</p>
<ul>
<li>Product structure is the skeleton, not changeful or complex.</li>
<li>Create from skeleton, not muscles.</li>
<li>Case: WeChat product structure.</li>
</ul>
<p>p50: The organic relationship between functional modules.</p>
<ul>
<li>Case: friend zone and album.</li>
<li>Don’t build multi-avatar for multi-avatar.</li>
</ul>
<p>p51: Design is classification</p>
<ul>
<li>Classification is how human brain recognizes patterns.</li>
<li>Classification is one way to simply complexities.</li>
<li>PM should think how to organize issues every day.</li>
<li>Case: WeChat always only have 4 bottom tabs.<br><img src="/images/wechat_p51.png" alt=""></li>
</ul>
<p>p52: Abstract so that we can simply complexities</p>
<ul>
<li>Abstract is to extract common features of things.</li>
<li>Abstract use simple model to cover varieties.</li>
<li>Highly abstract brings simplicity.</li>
<li>Case: the atomic items in friend zone content.</li>
<li>Case: one account to cover celebrity, artists, company, restaurants, online media, paper media, etc.</li>
</ul>
<p>p53: The easier the classification, the easier it gets accepted</p>
<ul>
<li>QQMail is not getting more complex</li>
<li>WeChat will upgrade, but the structure (and interface) will stay simple.</li>
</ul>
<p>p54: Find the core needs behind needs.</p>
<ul>
<li>Case: build grouping of contacts for friend zone?</li>
<li>Users say they want grouping, but the actual need is to block specific users.</li>
<li>In case you built grouping, few people will use.</li>
</ul>
<p>p55: Design based on scenarios, rather than feature list.</p>
<ul>
<li>“If you want feature X, buy a HTC/Samsung whatever instead” by Jony</li>
<li>Don’t put features altogether. Features serve scenarios and whole experience. No feature is independent.</li>
<li>Case: link keyboard, or wechat web?</li>
<li>Case: auto-play, or drive mode.</li>
</ul>
<p>p56: Make choices when facing scenarios.</p>
<ul>
<li>Online status? Mobile users are always online.</li>
<li>PC version? PC users could be offline, not as realtime as SMS.</li>
<li>Help people get rid of habit to say “88” (Chinese sound of bye) in QQ.</li>
</ul>
<p>p57: Keep features in the air (pony’s words)</p>
<ul>
<li>Case: Restaurant business plugin is invisible, it is only visible after user scan.</li>
<li>Unnoticable changes in new versions.</li>
<li>Only showcase new features for new users.</li>
</ul>
<p>p58: Differences between mobile and PC</p>
<ul>
<li>Mobile phones are extensions of human body. It is connected with human via all kinds of sensors. PC is outside things.</li>
<li>Mobile internet products are not basic migrations from PC to phone.</li>
<li>There won’t be this PPT without mobile phone. (It is from my evernote pieces where I type my ideas from time to time, which can’t be done on desktop.)</li>
<li>We build internet products with no web version.</li>
</ul>
<p>p59: Don’t over-design.</p>
<ul>
<li>The more you build, the more mistakes you make.</li>
<li>Polish the main trunk, don’t go too deep to the branches.</li>
<li>Case: nearby people.</li>
</ul>
<p>p60: We would rather sacrifice function instead of affecting experience.</p>
<ul>
<li>Don’t add entrances just for traffic.</li>
<li>Case: why can’t we add edit button on upper-left corner?</li>
</ul>
<p>p61: Product, or operation?</p>
<ul>
<li>Do things that make your work easier in the future.</li>
<li>Are you building a Class, or an Instance?</li>
<li>Good features don’t need regular additions, it can be done in one shot.</li>
<li>The differences between QQ floating bottle and WeChat floating bottle.</li>
<li>Good products will call the users. (pony’s words)</li>
</ul>
<p>p62: Let users drive users</p>
<ul>
<li>Rather than system admin</li>
<li>Case: how to make users setup avatars.</li>
</ul>
<p>p63: Extremely simple so that it can’t be surpassed.</p>
<ul>
<li>Case: Shaking. In my reply to pony: “Shaking is hard to be surpassed, because we have made it extremely simple.”</li>
</ul>
<p>p64: Design for screnarios in 2 years</p>
<ul>
<li>Case: Sent status? Network conditions should be good enough in next 2 years, so messages must can be sent successfully.</li>
</ul>
<p>p65: The responsiveness is No.1 experience.</p>
<ul>
<li>Case: the fluency of friend zone timeline</li>
</ul>
<p>p66: We would rather not to do it if the feature doesn’t excite us.</p>
<ul>
<li>You can’t really understand things which doesn’t excite you.</li>
<li>Curiosity drives PM.</li>
<li>The logic perfectness is also exciting.</li>
<li>Gain word of mouth from single points, rather than unnecessary features.</li>
<li>(Case: QQ Mailbox transfer station)</li>
</ul>
<p>p67: Keep the changes.</p>
<ul>
<li>Don’t do things in 1.0 which should be done in 2.0</li>
<li>For uncertainties, keep the change, don’t do it for now.</li>
<li>Launch is for verifying ideas, and it is a start of improvement.</li>
<li>Case: WeChat web, won’t be a product of complete features.</li>
<li>Case: feature to reply friend zone posts.</li>
</ul>
<p>p68: If there is no organic growth, no need to promote.</p>
<ul>
<li>It can only leave users bad impressions if we import users by force, and they will never come back.</li>
<li>KPI is side products of good products, and we should not change products for KPI.</li>
</ul>
<p>p69: Keep coarse, keep awkward.</p>
<ul>
<li>Put it aside if there is no better solution.</li>
<li>Case: the problem of sending message to a wrong group.</li>
<li>Case: group name card, group blocking.</li>
<li>Focus on big scenarios, ignore small ones.</li>
<li>If it is unimportant feature, put it in settings. But it’d be better if we don’t do it at all.</li>
</ul>
<p>p70: If the solution is too complicated, the problem must be wrong.</p>
<ul>
<li>Case: video chat.</li>
</ul>
<p>p71: Show your perception in every detail.</p>
<ul>
<li>Make sure you satisfy with every detail.</li>
<li>It is good enough if you are satisfied? Depends on your level.</li>
<li>Case: “from iPhone” or “from Shenzhen”</li>
</ul>
<p>p72: Give user the choices</p>
<ul>
<li>Except core concept, build others as detachable plugins.</li>
<li>Keep it simple.</li>
</ul>
<p>p73: Respect your users.</p>
<ul>
<li>Protect user privacy (ask user to confirm before uploading contacts, let user know if LBS location is exposed)</li>
<li>Don’t induce users.</li>
<li>Weigh user on every experience point. Case: add protection for user-input content in edit column in case of crash.</li>
<li>Case: use real PM signature in system messages, instead of “system admin” which is a machine-like thinking.</li>
</ul>
<p>p74: Only one version for the world.</p>
<ul>
<li>Case: mailbox.</li>
<li>Case: i18n of WeChat. WeChat won’t push localization versions for each region, but keep only one version for the global.</li>
</ul>
<p>p75: Build user experiences to extremes is also innovation. (pony’s words)</p>
<ul>
<li>Experiment of putting it close to ears. Why the screen won’t switch to earphone when we use hands to cover iPhone screen, but the ears can? Why WeChat can detect your ears?</li>
</ul>
<p>p76: Your values (attitudes) determines product features.</p>
<ul>
<li>How to decide whether to build photo filters and how to?</li>
<li>Rational analysis is about material gain which is not perfect.</li>
<li>It depends on your attitude to photos. Will everyday photos be more beautiful with or without filters?</li>
</ul>
<p>p77: Change user habits</p>
<ul>
<li>Phone is used to annoy people in past 100+ years after it was invented.</li>
<li>WeChat has video chat, but it won’t ring people up in a sudden.</li>
<li>You can’t reinvent phones, but you can change how people make calls.</li>
<li>New habits make user more comfortable.</li>
</ul>
<p>p78: Get rid of anti-human innovations</p>
<ul>
<li>Innovation is not based on inference.</li>
<li>Innovation serves people.</li>
<li>“Should you do anything to show intelligence, or choose virtue?” by Bezos.</li>
<li>Case: How about push once to speak instead of hold? It is unacceptable.</li>
</ul>
<p>p78: Don’t let strategy behaviour take the palce of true needs.</p>
<ul>
<li>Avoid “build through”. The needs which needs to be built through is no longer needs.</li>
<li>Avoid “integrate”. The needs which needs integration are sunset needs.</li>
<li>Avoid “pull up”. The needs which needs “pull up” is like KPI.</li>
<li>Avoid “import”. The needs which needs importing is no longer live.</li>
<li>Avoid “multi-platform”. Don’t do multi-platform for multi-platform.</li>
<li>Avoid “everything”. The things which cover everything is mediocre.</li>
</ul>
<p>p80: Start from people to change business patterns.</p>
<ul>
<li>Let the brand broadcast via friends.</li>
<li>Media is going eletronic.</li>
<li>How celebrities talk with people one by one.</li>
</ul>
<p>p81: There is no design but problem solving.</p>
<ul>
<li>Don’t lead by design.</li>
<li>Lead by users.</li>
</ul>
<p>p82: Innovate, or copy?</p>
<ul>
<li>You can’t reinvent phones.</li>
<li>But everything you do can be new.</li>
<li>Follow your users rather than competitive products.</li>
<li>Let products talk.</li>
</ul>
<p>p83: The evolvement story of friend zone</p>
<ul>
<li>Repeat all kinds of PK scenarios.</li>
<li>Simulate the massive behaviours after the crowd enters the scenarios in your mind.</li>
<li>Find the keys, give up branches (comments, replies, grouping and blocking)</li>
</ul>
<p>p84: Chapter of Nature</p>
<p>p85: Views on Nature</p>
<ul>
<li>Nature is human instinct behaviours and psychological reactions.</li>
<li>Inspiration on products: simple and no need rethinking.</li>
</ul>
<p>p86: Phase out technology thinking</p>
<ul>
<li>See how iOS hides technology: File? Folder? Uninstall? Process?</li>
<li>The complex technology should be hidden behind extremely simple use cases.</li>
<li>Products are built with rationals, but we use products to express emotions.</li>
<li>Don’t use word “support” in product instructions.</li>
<li>“Support XXX feature” is an outdated product expression.</li>
</ul>
<p>p87: Shaking: a chained natural effects.</p>
<p>p88: Let interaction simulates the nature.</p>
<ul>
<li>Build animation effects close to nature: the animation in friend zone comments.</li>
<li>Interaction is to gain feedbacks. Produce feedbacks as many as possible.</li>
<li>Generate natural and easy-to-understand feedbacks.</li>
</ul>
<p>p89: Single path</p>
<ul>
<li>A longer path with certainty is better than providing multiple paths which need users to think.</li>
<li>Home key</li>
<li>Shortcuts are not important but unreliable.</li>
<li>Don’t combine multiple functions in one operation as it increases complexity.</li>
</ul>
<p>p90: “Cool” is the future experience direction</p>
<ul>
<li>Cool is natural and simple</li>
<li>Case: grab photos from the air</li>
</ul>
<p>p91: Build features which can be learnt in 3 seconds</p>
<ul>
<li>Remove all text instructions (at least hide them)</li>
<li>Case: instruction illustration for shaking</li>
<li>Clarity and easy-to-understand win all decorations.</li>
</ul>
<p>p92: “Management” is unnatural</p>
<ul>
<li>Don’t involve user into management.</li>
<li>Calendar?</li>
<li>Grouping in contacts? (Weibo grouping, Google+)</li>
</ul>
<p>p93: Single clue is the most beautiful one.</p>
<ul>
<li>1D &gt; 2D</li>
<li>Twitter and Weibo timeline represent 1D</li>
<li>1D for mailbox? How about reading mails like Twitter?</li>
<li>Try not to use tab or dropdown list in mobile screens as it adds dimension.</li>
<li>How about Facebook’s sliding “drawer” design.</li>
</ul>
<p>p94: Changing skins (themes) shows inconfidence</p>
<ul>
<li>It shows inconfidence on default skin and loses visual brand effect (except products like weico app whose selling point is personalized design).</li>
<li>Focus on default skin.</li>
</ul>
<p>p95: Don’t let user choose</p>
<ul>
<li>Provide only one most general pattern.</li>
<li>Don’t provide alternative solutions to choose (like cascading and waterfalls)</li>
<li>Every additional choice confuses user and brings uncertainty.</li>
</ul>
<p>p96: Again, why there is no “sent” or “read”?</p>
<ul>
<li>If we need to look back to see if the message was sent, delivered, or read after we send every message, it is too much a burden and unacceptable.</li>
<li>Messages with tails are not simple or natural.</li>
<li>Nature is an instinct.</li>
</ul>
<p>p97: Fewer is better than more.</p>
<ul>
<li>Too much content breaks community atmosphere.</li>
<li>Too many friends create social terror.</li>
<li>Too much attention leads to unattractiveness.</li>
<li>Case: WeChat won’t import phone contacts or QQ friends.</li>
<li>Case: friend zone won’t import QQ Zone blogs.</li>
</ul>
<p>p98: 100 Millions is just one user</p>
<ul>
<li>They are the same.</li>
<li>You can simulate them naturally if you listen to their needs widely and understand their needs.</li>
<li>You will know their feelings.</li>
<li>Keep the 100 Million users in your heart.</li>
</ul>
<p>p99: Switch to a dummy user in one second.</p>
<ul>
<li>Train yourself the ability to switch to a dummy user in one second.</li>
<li>Know how people use products via large amounts of CE</li>
<li>Experience the products as a dummy user so that you can find the problems.</li>
<li>Focus on first-time experience, because you can’t find new problems once you are familiar with the product.</li>
</ul>
<p>p100: Train your instinct on the nature</p>
<ul>
<li>Form instinct by analyzing thousands of problems.</li>
<li>Empty your previous experience, look the world in more instinct eyes. Like to phrase out the favor of technology.</li>
<li>The solution of complex problems may not come from induction but from intuition.</li>
</ul>
<p>p101: PM’s mentality</p>
<ul>
<li>Fight for knowledge, not pride.</li>
<li>Give up emotions to know the problem deeper.</li>
<li>You shortcomings could be your strengths. E.g. people who fear social may know how to make social products.</li>
</ul>
<p>p102: Chapter of Quality</p>
<p>p103: Ambition to change the old world.</p>
<ul>
<li>My only expectation on iPhone5 is that it doesn’t support phones just like iPad (3G). So that I can save on phone bills. But you can text me via kik, call me via Google Voice, video chat via facetime.</li>
<li>On the last day before WeChat project proposal.</li>
</ul>
<p>p104: Have your own ideas and wishes</p>
<ul>
<li>WeChat is “a new life style”.</li>
<li>It determines the altitude of your products.</li>
<li>Your altitude will be reflected in every detail, unavoidably. </li>
</ul>
<p>p105: WeChat is “a life style”</p>
<ul>
<li>It is “a”, rather than “one kind of”.</li>
<li>It is the difference between WeChat and QQ.</li>
</ul>
<p>p106: QQ Mailbox: Keep in touch.</p>
<p>p107: Convey culture minds via tech products.</p>
<ul>
<li>One thousand people have one thousand feelings.</li>
<li>Wechat startup pictures.</li>
</ul>
<p>p108: “Send fewer WeChat messages”</p>
<ul>
<li>What else products ask users to use less? (Besides cigaretts)</li>
<li>It reflects your understanding level on products and users.</li>
<li>Don’t build it for marketing. Because it will have marketing effects itself.</li>
</ul>
<p>p109: Make the welcome page as your product release conference.</p>
<ul>
<li>New features list shows a tech mindset.</li>
<li>Don’t do product release conference.</li>
<li>Every welcome page is a story.</li>
<li>It is one of the fewer places where you can express feelings.</li>
<li>Make the product worth expecting.</li>
</ul>
<p>p110: Programmers who don’t listen to rock music are not good PM</p>
<ul>
<li>Rock shows anti-tradition, humanity, freedom, etc.</li>
<li>Rock helps us find instinct status. Such status will be reflected in products.</li>
<li>Story of Pink Floyd and MJ.</li>
<li>“We won’t give you gift iPad!”</li>
<li>Keep special minds, do special things.</li>
</ul>
<p>p111: Advertise which is human friendly</p>
<ul>
<li>Don’t advertise for advertisement.</li>
<li>Feelings from users are the best. (Many are from user original words in weibo, like “WeChat: Make voice coquettish again.”)</li>
<li>The WeChat ads in mailbox.</li>
</ul>
<p>p112:<br><img src="/images/wechat_p112.png" alt=""></p>
<p>p113:<br><img src="/images/wechat_p113.png" alt=""></p>
<p>p114: Find best partners.</p>
<ul>
<li>Tuzki</li>
<li>Photographers of National Geography</li>
<li>Nike</li>
</ul>
<p>p115:<br><img src="/images/wechat_p115.png" alt=""></p>
<p>p116: Words reflect personal quality.</p>
<ul>
<li>Words in products is talking to users. It reflects your quality.</li>
<li>Easy-to-understand shows your have clear minds.</li>
<li>Don’t ingratiate users or play yourself up. Treat users as friends.</li>
<li>Case: reminder before posting photos, login.</li>
</ul>
<p>p117: Some words to avoid.</p>
<ul>
<li>Chinese “ba”.</li>
<li>Chinese “oh”.</li>
<li>Force user do things reluctantly. (“Why don’t you invite friends now?””)</li>
<li>Success. (“You have saved it successfully.” Could they fail to save?)</li>
<li>Chinese version of “you” which shows respect.</li>
</ul>
<p>p118: Feeling of Future</p>
<ul>
<li>Visual keywords: future, tech, abstract, simple.</li>
<li>Forget Chinese elements.</li>
<li>Abstract or simulate reality?</li>
<li>You can only apply it once you feel the beauty of simplicity.</li>
<li>Shall we show blue sky and white cloud when video chatting in Beijing? (luke and pony’s opinions)</li>
</ul>
<p>p119: Do you have competitors or not?</p>
<ul>
<li>Most important thing is what do you want. Rather than what others are doing.</li>
<li>WeChat has no competitors, and we don’t analyze competitors.</li>
<li>They are not our PM.</li>
<li>We would rather focus the future instead of focus on peers.</li>
</ul>
<p>p120: Works, not products.</p>
<ul>
<li>Works will beat material gain products. (Steve Jobs comments on the race with Microsoft in this way.)</li>
<li>Works are longing for perfection.</li>
</ul>
<p>p121: Artisan, not designers.</p>
<ul>
<li>Optimize 10 details every day (the inconvenient parts which you and surrounding people experienced)</li>
<li>Every detail which you did is creation which includes your views, ideas and choices on implementations.</li>
<li>Don’t talk about design out of nothing.</li>
</ul>
<p>p122: Build products with soul</p>
<ul>
<li>Soul: organically connected structure (product structure), with muscle (features), with quality (values), agile response (high speed), rationals (clear logic, reasonable interactions), speaking (copywriting).</li>
<li>Just like a human, it is complete and in a harmony, and it’s not a Schizy.</li>
<li>Products have personality. It may not be perfect, but it should be elegant from outside, harmonious inside, like artwork.</li>
</ul>
<p>p123: Free individuals</p>
<ul>
<li>Internet products should make individual more free.</li>
<li>How should we change weibo comment system?</li>
<li>Personalized longtail product is the future.</li>
<li>Industrilization satisfies low cost, personalization creates special value.</li>
</ul>
<p>p124: Chapter of UI</p>
<p>p125: UI is to talk to users by products.</p>
<p>p126: Forbid use of competitor products</p>
<ul>
<li>UI designers are forbidden to use competitor products so they won’t be misled.</li>
<li>PM can use, but shouldn’t use much.</li>
</ul>
<p>p127: UI focuses features, not the other way around.</p>
<ul>
<li>Features come first before UI.</li>
<li>Don’t change scenario or feature just for a better UI idea.</li>
</ul>
<p>p128: Being organized wins visual display.</p>
<ul>
<li>Classification, and classification!</li>
<li>Cascading relationship shows classification.</li>
<li>Being organized is more important than being convenient.</li>
<li>Case: input box in dialogue, one line or two line?</li>
</ul>
<p>p129: Should there be only pattern.</p>
<ul>
<li>To keep consistency in a application, we should only allow one font, one control, one pattern and one background … </li>
<li>Various displays confuse user.</li>
<li>Try to use standard interfaces.</li>
<li>Being reasonable is more important than personality.</li>
</ul>
<p>p130: One theme in every interface.</p>
<ul>
<li>Photography principle: every photo should have only one theme.</li>
<li>Don’t use bi-column interface.</li>
<li>Highlight themes.</li>
</ul>
<p>p131: Every dialogue box has a highlighted default button</p>
<ul>
<li>Don’t make me think.</li>
<li>Case: send original picture is confusing. </li>
</ul>
<p>p132: Keep improving most frequent operations.</p>
<ul>
<li>The smoothness of auto pulling for scrolling back to the top.</li>
<li>Evolvement of chat background</li>
</ul>
<p>p133: Features which need text instruction is not good experience.</p>
<ul>
<li>Don’t assume people will read text instructions.</li>
<li>Don’t assume user will study background.</li>
<li>Be able to use even without explaining.</li>
<li>Use less tips which are like patches.</li>
</ul>
<p>p134: Hide numbers.</p>
<ul>
<li>N photos</li>
<li>N contacts</li>
<li>78.56% downloading</li>
</ul>
<p>p135: Explore new interactions on phones</p>
<ul>
<li>Phones are often used on the go.</li>
<li>Phones are extensions of the body and have more sensors.</li>
<li>Case: how to recognize people in the house.</li>
<li>Case: auto scaling down when showing friend zone photos.</li>
</ul>
<p>p136: Practice your aesthetic。</p>
<ul>
<li>The aesthetic of your product won’t surpass your own aesthetic.</li>
<li>Every detail shows your aesthetic.</li>
<li>Case: pulling down running wheel in friend zone.</li>
<li>Case: simple beauty. </li>
</ul>
<p>p137: Thanks!</p>
<p>p138: What I said above are all wrong.</p>
<p>p139: Product Views behind WeChat</p>
<ul>
<li>Allen Zhang (Xiaolong Zhang), August 2012.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="2016/04/12/product-views-behind-wechat/">Click here for Chinese version</a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;《Product Views Behind WeChat》 is written by Xiaolong (Allen) Zhang, the founding father of WeChat. The work came from a special internal 
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Tech" scheme="http://zhesong.info/categories/Tech/"/>
    
    
      <category term="English" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/English/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>微信背后的产品观 中英文版</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2016/04/13/product-views-behind-wechat/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2016/04/13/product-views-behind-wechat/</id>
    <published>2016-04-13T03:00:04.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T08:32:01.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>《微信背后的产品观》，作者，张小龙，微信之父。这个作品来自于2012年7月24日腾讯内部的一次特别讲座，用时8小时20分，PPT 180余页。除去保密部分，流出版PPT 139页。本文将PPT图文整理成长文，同时翻译发布英文版。</p>
<p>文章最后是英文版链接。</p>
<p>p1:<br>微信背后的产品观<br>原作： 张小龙</p>
<p>p2:</p>
<ul>
<li>微信回顾</li>
<li>用户篇</li>
<li>需求篇</li>
<li>设计篇</li>
<li>气质篇</li>
<li>UI篇</li>
</ul>
<p>p3: 微信回顾</p>
<ul>
<li>433天，一亿用户</li>
<li>成为移动互联网的新入口</li>
</ul>
<p>p4:<br>启动<br>（2010年11月19日）<br>用户数突破1亿<br>1.0 1月26日<br>2.0 5月10日 语音对讲<br>2.5 8月3日 查看附近人<br>3.0 10月1日 摇一摇 漂流瓶<br>3.5 12月20日 二维码<br>4.0 4月19日 朋友圈 开放接口<br>4.2 7月19日 语音通话 视频通话</p>
<p>p5: 产品经理是站在上帝身边的人</p>
<ul>
<li>了解人性</li>
<li>了解群体心理</li>
<li>产品经理像上帝一样，建造系统并制定规则，让群体在系统中演化。</li>
</ul>
<p>p6: 认识环境的反应器</p>
<ul>
<li>我的实验：在路上和在电脑前发微博的区别：电脑屏幕（微博本身，内容）也是环境</li>
<li>微博上follow的人就是你的世界</li>
<li>朋友圈的拍照和Qzone相册的区别</li>
<li>产品营造环境，决定用户反应</li>
</ul>
<p>p7: 人是懒惰的</p>
<ul>
<li>懒惰导致发明</li>
<li>懒惰是创新的动力</li>
<li>案例：语音查找联系人</li>
</ul>
<p>p8: 时尚是驱动力</p>
<ul>
<li>“因为别人都在用”</li>
<li>人是跟风的</li>
<li>在互联网产品中，“时尚”是重要驱动力</li>
<li>不要太“工具化”</li>
</ul>
<p>p9: 人没有耐心</p>
<ul>
<li>用户没有耐心看你的说明书</li>
<li>如果不能让用户一分钟爱上你</li>
<li>产品做好前不要轻易拉用户来你的产品</li>
</ul>
<p>p10: 人不爱学习</p>
<ul>
<li>博客的衰落。RSS？</li>
<li>马桶阅读理论：不要给用户超过马桶上看不完的内容</li>
</ul>
<p>p11: 用户是乌合之众</p>
<ul>
<li>《乌合之众》</li>
<li>群体智商低于个体智商</li>
<li>互联网产品的用户是群体，不是个人</li>
<li>不用用对待个体的方式来对待群体，尤其是互联网产品</li>
</ul>
<p>p12: 重视“屌丝”用户群</p>
<ul>
<li>#日有所思# facebook, pinterest, instagram, path等产品解决了人的“存在感”的问题。存在感是指人离开了SNS就觉得自己与人群脱节被孤立而无价值。这些产品在中国不能普及，因为中国人面临的问题比存在感还低一个层次，是“生存感”。但中国有这样一个群体，他们既有生存感的压力，又有存在感的渴望，这群人就是“屌丝”。中国互联网的主题用户心理和需求，应从了解屌丝群生存和心理状态入手，搞清了屌丝，就把握住了用户群。</li>
</ul>
<p>p13: 从日常体验中发现本质</p>
<ul>
<li>Galaxy Note: 时尚？方便长指甲打字。</li>
<li>触碰开关。比普通开关更贴近人的情感。</li>
<li>伟大的产品应该满足人的情感需求。</li>
</ul>
<p>p14: 让不上微博的用户来用你的产品</p>
<ul>
<li>他们才是主题用户群，懒到连微博都不上的。</li>
<li>他们就在你的身边</li>
<li>时刻想到，他们才是你的用户</li>
</ul>
<p>p15: 人性化即是以己推人</p>
<ul>
<li>你无法理解他人，只能理解自己</li>
<li>你需要了解人最普遍的心理活动</li>
</ul>
<p>p16: 需求是满足人们的贪嗔痴</p>
<ul>
<li>产品的终极目标是满足人性需求</li>
<li>不在产品中掺和自己的道德感</li>
<li>满足贪嗔痴，但又要用户“少发微信”。世界是荒诞的。</li>
<li>“产品是技术和艺术的结合” Steve Jobs</li>
</ul>
<p>p17: 对新点子，99%的情况下否定是对的</p>
<ul>
<li>大部分“我有个好主意”都是脱离需求的</li>
<li>不臆想需求</li>
</ul>
<p>p18: 不要用户说要什么就做什么</p>
<ul>
<li>不直接满足用户需求</li>
<li>用户需求是零散的，解决方案是归纳抽象的过程。</li>
<li>用户反馈只是帮助你了解到他们的想法</li>
</ul>
<p>p19: 大部分新功能是可以砍掉的。</p>
<ul>
<li>回顾一下，你们做了多少功能，是可以不做的。</li>
</ul>
<p>p20: 不从同类产品里找需求</p>
<ul>
<li>涂鸦重要吗？</li>
<li>从别的产品里，你无法深刻理解需求。</li>
</ul>
<p>p21: 不要听从产品经理的需求</p>
<ul>
<li>他们不是用户却以为代表用户</li>
<li>他们的分析过于理性</li>
<li>他们会要求你加是否在线，是否已发送到手机，是否已读，要分组，要滤镜，要涂鸦，要多终端同步，要云端保存消息，要文字图片视频一起发timeline，要多头像，要赞头像，要有PC版，要自动导入通讯录好友，要群名片，要…… “你去用其他同类产品吧”</li>
</ul>
<p>p22: 需求只来自你对用户的了解</p>
<ul>
<li>需求不来自调研</li>
<li>需求不来自分析</li>
<li>需求不来自讨论</li>
<li>需求不来自竞争对手</li>
</ul>
<p>p23: 从微博上感受用户潮流</p>
<ul>
<li>每天花一小时看普通用户在微博上讨论他们是如何用你的产品的</li>
<li>他们的场景，感受等</li>
<li>他们所处的时代潮流往哪里走</li>
<li>忽略评论家意见</li>
<li>等待他们说“太好玩了”</li>
</ul>
<p>p24: 从用户讨论中发现灵感</p>
<ul>
<li>微博上的用户帖子，才是真实场景的反应</li>
<li>案例：石头剪子布的故事</li>
<li>已经没有什么可以阻止人类使用微信语音玩石头、剪子、布了</li>
</ul>
<p>p25: 每个时代都有每个时代的产品</p>
<ul>
<li>对时代潮流保持敏锐</li>
<li>从QQ到微信</li>
</ul>
<p>p26: 满足自己的需求由于满足用户需求</p>
<ul>
<li>你无法真正理解他人</li>
<li>你无法满足海量的个体的个性需求</li>
<li>人同此心，从自身捕获大众需求</li>
<li>案例：已阅读</li>
<li>案例：语音写提醒，语音找人</li>
</ul>
<p>p27: 找到需求背后的心理诉求</p>
<ul>
<li>需求本质往往可以归结为心理诉求</li>
<li>漂流瓶：满足倾诉，好奇的心理。这是一个心理驱动的范例。人民的倾诉欲望是如此之强，不弱mail</li>
<li>如果为做交友而做漂流瓶，会把握不到本质（案例：发漂流瓶，还是文字？）</li>
</ul>
<p>p28: 心理满足的驱动力远胜工具甚至省钱</p>
<ul>
<li>省钱的短信替代工具不会成功。如果定位于更省钱的工具，可能就麻烦了</li>
<li>微信不是QQ，“微信，不只是一个通信工具”</li>
<li>微信是一个生活方式，反映的是心理满足至上</li>
</ul>
<p>p29: “爽”胜过功能</p>
<ul>
<li>爽！（营销的目的是让用户觉得“爽”）</li>
<li>好玩！（微博评论说“好玩”就对了）</li>
<li>口碑传播的基础是“好玩”</li>
<li>爽是体验。体验比功能更易传播</li>
</ul>
<p>p30: 为群体效应而做：附近的人</p>
<ul>
<li>案例：附近的人</li>
<li>不是为了陌生人交友，是为了好奇心</li>
<li>他们会发生什么？</li>
<li>它是有群体效应的，每个人在观察别人，也在被观察。</li>
<li>他们第一次在现实中大规模互相看到</li>
</ul>
<p>p31: 为群体效应而做：摇一摇</p>
<ul>
<li>人们会喜欢简单的行为动作</li>
<li>人们会对随机好奇</li>
<li>人们会对跨空间的同类好奇</li>
<li>它有群体效应</li>
</ul>
<p>p32: 为想法而做：朋友圈</p>
<ul>
<li>想法：人人需要在朋友关注中获得存在感，照片是手机最佳互动载体，人只需要三五好友，人需要不暴露好友但又要扎堆</li>
<li>一种比facebook，path更私密的社区</li>
<li>想法比功能重要</li>
<li>为自己要用而做</li>
</ul>
<p>p33: 只抓主场景，不做全功能</p>
<ul>
<li>做大而全很容易，做少很难</li>
<li>如果没有化繁为简的能力，就克制自己的做多的欲望</li>
<li>做多源于不自信</li>
<li>每天看到几个需求的爽，远大于提出几个需求</li>
<li>案例：朋友圈只能发照片。发140字的难度远胜一张图片</li>
</ul>
<p>p34: 不要从战略分析来逆推需求</p>
<ul>
<li>Microsoft, Nokia, Google</li>
</ul>
<p>p35: 调研获得需求是骗人的</p>
<ul>
<li>从大量反馈看出需求是骗人的（群的需求，用户会告诉你他们需求的是QQ群）</li>
<li>用户反馈能帮助完善体验，但不会告诉你要做什么新东西</li>
<li>从数据统计看出需求更是骗人的</li>
</ul>
<p>p36: 需求来自对群体效应的好奇</p>
<ul>
<li>漂流瓶</li>
<li>附近的人</li>
<li>摇一摇</li>
</ul>
<p>p37: 需求来自于自身需要和周边朋友反馈</p>
<ul>
<li>蓝牙支持</li>
<li>Web微信</li>
<li>待办置顶</li>
<li>换手机迁移</li>
</ul>
<p>p38: 需求来自对当下生活潮流的理解</p>
<ul>
<li>朋友圈：人们需要从和朋友的互动中很安全地找到存在感，并且很舒适</li>
</ul>
<p>p39: 需求来自对平台的理解</p>
<ul>
<li>开放平台的接口很美</li>
<li>开放平台的生态很诱人</li>
<li>开放平台带来的不确定性令人期盼</li>
<li>生态系统，而非单独产品</li>
</ul>
<p>p40: 需求来自对信息流的理解</p>
<ul>
<li>订阅平台：让所有信息成为可Push的</li>
<li>让个体都能显现</li>
<li>让品牌通过朋友传播</li>
</ul>
<p>p41:<br><img src="/images/wechat_p41.png" alt=""></p>
<p>p42: 需求来自于建立新系统</p>
<ul>
<li>让二维码普及起来，成为入口</li>
<li>通过建立简单的规则，创作一个自运行系统，满足人群的某种心理或经济需要</li>
</ul>
<p>p43: 在最后一刻才决定新版本特性</p>
<ul>
<li>不预先规划版本功能，一个版本做完了，才确定下个版本的需求</li>
<li>长期在脑袋中酝酿各种可能的特性</li>
<li>重要的需求会在合适的时间自己浮现</li>
<li>案例：附近的人</li>
</ul>
<p>p44: 世界是新的</p>
<ul>
<li>忘记过去的数据甚至经验</li>
<li>对当前和未来的趋势的洞察才重要</li>
<li>PC上的入口在搜索框，手机上的入口在二维码</li>
</ul>
<p>p45: 产品是演化出来的，而非规划出来的</p>
<ul>
<li>微信的每个版本该做什么，都是等上个版本发布后才确定的</li>
<li>我们不可能知道半年后的产品形态。规划是骗人的</li>
<li>每个版本的确定越后越好，取决于当时的整体用户环境，以及对当下环境的判断</li>
</ul>
<p>p46: 有DNA的产品才会演化</p>
<ul>
<li>DNA是产品的价值观，认知</li>
<li>如果将产品比喻为生命体的话，它是由DNA的</li>
</ul>
<p>p47: 群体效应是社交产品的核心</p>
<ul>
<li>通过对人内心欲望的洞察，建立虚拟社会的规则，引发群体效应， 群体在推动规则变化</li>
<li>案例：如何调戏明星？</li>
</ul>
<p>p48: 将用户分为高中低端是不道德的</p>
<ul>
<li>做人人都爱用的产品</li>
<li>通用产品做得低龄化是不专业的体验</li>
<li>产品面前，人人平等<br><img src="/images/wechat_p48.png" alt=""></li>
</ul>
<p>p49: 先做产品结构，之后才是功能细节</p>
<ul>
<li>产品结构是骨骼，不可多变和复杂</li>
<li>创作从骨骼开始，而不是先造肌肉</li>
<li>案例：微信的产品结构</li>
</ul>
<p>p50: 功能模块之间是有机联系的关系</p>
<ul>
<li>案例：朋友圈和个人相册</li>
<li>不为多头像而多头像</li>
</ul>
<p>p51: 设计就是分类</p>
<ul>
<li>分类是人类大脑的识别模式</li>
<li>分类是化繁为简的方法之一</li>
<li>PM每天都应思考如何让事情更有条理</li>
<li>案例：微信保证只有四个底部tab<br><img src="/images/wechat_p51.png" alt=""></li>
</ul>
<p>p52: 抽象方能化繁为简</p>
<ul>
<li>抽象是提取实物的共有特性</li>
<li>抽象使得用简单模型覆盖多样性</li>
<li>高度抽象带来简单化</li>
<li>案例：朋友圈内容的原子颗粒</li>
<li>案例：一个认证账号，覆盖名人，艺人，企业，餐饮，网媒，平媒等</li>
</ul>
<p>p53: 越简单的分类越易于被接受</p>
<ul>
<li>QQMail没有变复杂</li>
<li>微信会升级，但结构（和界面）会保持简单</li>
</ul>
<p>p54: 找到需求背后的本质需求</p>
<ul>
<li>案例：朋友圈该在通讯录里做分组吗？</li>
<li>用户说要分组，但屏蔽几个人才是需求</li>
<li>如果你做了分组，又没人用了</li>
</ul>
<p>p55: 面向场景来做设计，而非功能列表</p>
<ul>
<li>“if you want feature X, buy a HTC/Samsung whatever instead” by Jony</li>
<li>不堆砌功能。功能服务于场景和整体体验。没有孤立的功能。</li>
<li>案例：链接键盘，还是web微信</li>
<li>案例：自动播放，还是驾驶模式</li>
</ul>
<p>p56: 面向场景，才能取舍</p>
<ul>
<li>在线状态？手机是永远在线的</li>
<li>PC版？PC版会离线，无法像短信一样实时</li>
<li>去除人们在QQ上说“88”的习惯</li>
</ul>
<p>p57: 让功能存在于无形之中（pony语）</p>
<ul>
<li>案例：餐饮商家插件不可见，扫描才有</li>
<li>让新版看不出有变化</li>
<li>只有新手才将所有（新）功能罗列在显眼的地方</li>
</ul>
<p>p58: 手机和PC的区别</p>
<ul>
<li>手机是肢体的延伸，手机和人是一体的（通过各种传感器）。PC是外物，即外部环境。</li>
<li>移动互联网产品不是简单的PC到手机的移植</li>
<li>如果没有手机，就没有这份PPT。（采用Evernote随时在手机上记录想法，电脑做不到）</li>
<li>做没有web的移动互联网产品</li>
</ul>
<p>p59: 不过度设计</p>
<ul>
<li>做得越多可能错得越多</li>
<li>对主干精雕细琢，对枝叶不做深究</li>
<li>案例：附近的人</li>
</ul>
<p>p60: 宁愿损失功能也不损失体验</p>
<ul>
<li>不为了流量而到处加入口</li>
<li>案例：会话界面左上角的编辑按钮，为什么不可以有？</li>
</ul>
<p>p61: 产品，还是运营？</p>
<ul>
<li>做一劳永逸的事情</li>
<li>你在做Class（类型），还是在做Instance（实例）？</li>
<li>好特性不需要不断做加法，一次成型</li>
<li>邮箱漂流瓶和微信漂流瓶的不同</li>
<li>好产品会召唤用户（pony语）</li>
</ul>
<p>p62: 让用户推动用户</p>
<ul>
<li>而非系统管理员来推动</li>
<li>案例：如何让用户设置头像</li>
</ul>
<p>p63: 极简方能不被超越</p>
<ul>
<li>案例：摇一摇。于pony的回信中，“摇一摇很难被超越，因为我们已经做到极简”。</li>
</ul>
<p>p64: 面向两年后的场景来设计</p>
<ul>
<li>案例：已送达状态？2年后网络状况足够好，必然是能送达的。</li>
</ul>
<p>p65: 操作的响应速度永远是第一体验</p>
<ul>
<li>案例：朋友圈的timeline的流畅度</li>
</ul>
<p>p66: 如果一个特性不能让人兴奋，不如不做</p>
<ul>
<li>你不能真正理解自己不感兴趣的需求</li>
<li>好奇心是PM的驱动力</li>
<li>逻辑的完美也是令人兴奋的</li>
<li>在单点获得口碑，而不是一些可有可无的特性</li>
<li>（案例：QQ邮箱中转站）</li>
</ul>
<p>p67: 保留变化</p>
<ul>
<li>不在1.0做2.0该做的</li>
<li>对不确定的，保留变化余地，先不做</li>
<li>上线是为了验证想法，是改进的开始</li>
<li>案例：web微信，不做大而全</li>
<li>案例：朋友圈评论的回复</li>
</ul>
<p>p68: 如果没有自然增长，就不必推广</p>
<ul>
<li>硬导入用户，只会给用户留下坏印象，以后再也不来了</li>
<li>KPI是好的产品的副产品，不为KPI而改变产品</li>
</ul>
<p>p69: 保持粗放，保持笨拙</p>
<ul>
<li>如果没有好的解决方案，就先放着不做</li>
<li>案例：发错群的问题</li>
<li>案例：群名片，群屏蔽</li>
<li>抓大场景，忽略小场景</li>
<li>非重要特性就放到设置里，放到设置里不如不做</li>
</ul>
<p>p70: 如果解决方案非常复杂，一定是问题错了</p>
<ul>
<li>案例：视频通话</li>
</ul>
<p>p71: 在每个细节中体现认知</p>
<ul>
<li>每一个细节都做到自己满意</li>
<li>满意是否就好：取决于你的水准</li>
<li>案例：“来自iPhone”和来自“深圳”</li>
</ul>
<p>p72: 给用户选择权</p>
<ul>
<li>除了核心功能，都做成可卸载的插件</li>
<li>保持简单</li>
</ul>
<p>p73: 尊重用户</p>
<ul>
<li>保护用户隐私（通讯录上传要经过同意，LBS暴露位置要告知）</li>
<li>不诱导用户</li>
<li>在每个体验点上以用户为重。案例：在所有正文编辑处加上crash后的内容保护</li>
<li>案例：系统邮件，采用真实的产品经理签名，而非机器思维的“系统管理员”</li>
</ul>
<p>p74: 全球只做一个版本<br>案例：邮箱<br>案例：微信国际化。微信不会做各个地区的本地化版本，而保持全球一个版本</p>
<p>p75: 把用户体验做到极致就是创新（pony语）</p>
<ul>
<li>贴耳朵试验。用手遮挡iPhone屏幕为什么不会切换到听筒，而耳朵就可以？为什么微信能识别你的耳朵？</li>
</ul>
<p>p76: 你的价值观（态度）决定产品特性</p>
<ul>
<li>如何决定“是否做滤镜，怎么做？”</li>
<li>理性的分析是功利而不完美的</li>
<li>取决于你对照片的态度，生活照片是有滤镜更美，还是没有更美？</li>
</ul>
<p>p77: 改变用户习惯</p>
<ul>
<li>电话发明一百年来，都在骚扰人</li>
<li>微信视频通话，不允许突然呼叫别人</li>
<li>你无法重新发明电话，但可以改变打电话的方式</li>
<li>新的习惯，让用户更舒适</li>
</ul>
<p>p78: 抛弃不人性的创新</p>
<ul>
<li>创新不是基于推理</li>
<li>创新是为人服务的</li>
<li>“你要不计一切代价展示聪明，还是选择善良？” by 贝索斯</li>
<li>案例：耳机的按一下开始说话（而不是按住），是不能被接受的。</li>
</ul>
<p>p79: 避免战略行为替代真实需求</p>
<ul>
<li>避免“打通”。需要打通，说明不是需求</li>
<li>避免“整合”。需要整合，说明都不行了</li>
<li>避免“拉动”。需要拉动，说明是KPI了</li>
<li>避免“导入”。需要导入，说明没有生命力</li>
<li>避免“多平台”。不为平台而平台</li>
<li>避免“全面”。全面东西是平庸的</li>
</ul>
<p>p80: 从人出发，改变商业模式</p>
<ul>
<li>让品牌在朋友中传播</li>
<li>媒体的电子化</li>
<li>明星如何和人一一对话</li>
</ul>
<p>p81: 没有设计，只有解决问题</p>
<ul>
<li>不以设计为导向</li>
<li>以用户为导向</li>
</ul>
<p>p82: 创新，还是抄袭？</p>
<ul>
<li>你不可能重新发明电话</li>
<li>但你做的每件事情都可以是新的</li>
<li>跟随用户，而非业界产品</li>
<li>用产品来说话</li>
</ul>
<p>p83: 朋友圈的演化故事</p>
<ul>
<li>反复PK各种场景</li>
<li>在头脑中模拟群体进入后的集体行为</li>
<li>找到关键点，放弃枝叶（评论回复，分组，屏蔽）</li>
</ul>
<p>p84: 自然篇</p>
<p>p85: 自然观</p>
<ul>
<li>自然是人最本能的行为和心理反应</li>
<li>对产品的启发：简单，不用想</li>
</ul>
<p>p86: 去技术化思维</p>
<ul>
<li>看iOS是如何隐藏技术的：File? Folder？Uninstall？Process？ </li>
<li>复杂的技术要隐藏在极度易用性背后</li>
<li>产品是由理性搭建，却用来表达感性</li>
<li>产品介绍中不允许出现“支持”二字</li>
<li>“支持XX特性”，这是过时的产品表达</li>
</ul>
<p>p87: 摇一摇：一连串的自然反应</p>
<p>p88: 让交互模拟自然</p>
<ul>
<li>用动画效果逼近自然：朋友圈的评论弹出动画</li>
<li>交互就是获得反馈，尽可能产生反馈</li>
<li>产生自然易理解的反馈</li>
</ul>
<p>p89: 单一路径</p>
<ul>
<li>一个固定哪怕更长路径的操作，胜过提供几个但需要用户思考的路径</li>
<li>Home键</li>
<li>快捷方式不重要，且不可依赖</li>
<li>不把多个功能合并到一个操作里，会增加复杂度</li>
</ul>
<p>p90: “酷”是未来的体验方向</p>
<ul>
<li>酷是自然而简单的</li>
<li>案例：隔空抓图</li>
</ul>
<p>p91: 做三秒就会用的特性</p>
<ul>
<li>去掉一切文字说明（至少隐藏）</li>
<li>案例：摇一摇的说明图</li>
<li>清晰易懂胜过一切修饰</li>
</ul>
<p>p92: “管理”是不自然的</p>
<ul>
<li>不让用户卷入到“管理”工作里</li>
<li>日历？</li>
<li>通讯录分组？（微博分组，Google+）</li>
</ul>
<p>p93: 单线索最美</p>
<ul>
<li>一维胜过二维</li>
<li>Twitter，微博的timeline是一维的代表</li>
<li>邮件，能采用一维吗？像Twitter一样读邮件如何？</li>
<li>手机屏幕上，尽可能不在标题栏使用Tab/下拉框 增加维度</li>
<li>Facebook的滑动式“抽屉”设计怎么样</li>
</ul>
<p>p94: 换肤是不自信的体现</p>
<ul>
<li>缺乏对默认皮肤的信心，损失视觉品牌效果（weico等以个性设计为卖点的app除外）</li>
<li>专注做好默认皮肤</li>
</ul>
<p>p95: 不让用户选择</p>
<ul>
<li>只提供一种最通用模式</li>
<li>不提供可选的方案（如列表和瀑布可选）</li>
<li>每增加一种选择，都让用户迷惑。不固定感。</li>
</ul>
<p>p96: 再说为什么没有“已发送”“已阅读”</p>
<ul>
<li>发条消息还要回头看是否发出是否送达是否已阅是累赘而不可接受的</li>
<li>消息带尾巴是不简洁不自然的</li>
<li>自然是种直觉</li>
</ul>
<p>p97: 少比多更好</p>
<ul>
<li>内容太多会破坏社区氛围</li>
<li>朋友太多会导致社交恐惧</li>
<li>关注太多会导致缺乏吸引力</li>
<li>案例：微信不会批量导入手机通讯录和QQ好友</li>
<li>案例：朋友圈不会导入QQ空间日志</li>
</ul>
<p>p98: 一亿用户就是一个用户</p>
<ul>
<li>他们是相同的</li>
<li>你可以很“自然”地模拟成他们，如果你广泛听取他们的需要，理解他们的需要</li>
<li>你知道他们的喜怒哀乐</li>
<li>心怀一亿用户</li>
</ul>
<p>p99: 瞬间成为傻瓜用户</p>
<ul>
<li>训练自己瞬间成为傻瓜用户的能力</li>
<li>通过大量CE来了解人们是如何用产品的</li>
<li>从傻瓜用户的角度来体验产品，才能发现问题</li>
<li>注重第一次体验的感觉，用熟了就不能发现问题了</li>
</ul>
<p>p100: 锻炼对“自然”的直觉</p>
<ul>
<li>通过对成千问题的分析来形成直觉</li>
<li>倒空自己的过往经验，以更本性的眼光看世界。比如技术控的去除</li>
<li>对复杂问题的解决，可能不来自推理，而是直觉</li>
</ul>
<p>p101: PM的心态</p>
<ul>
<li>求知，不为自尊心而战</li>
<li>放下情绪，才能深入问题本质</li>
<li>用数据和调研来说话</li>
<li>你的短板可能就是你的强项。比如，社交恐惧者可能知道怎么做社交产品</li>
</ul>
<p>p102: 气质篇</p>
<p>p103: 改变旧世界的意愿</p>
<ul>
<li>我对iPhone5的唯一期待是，像iPad（3G）一样，不支持电话功能。这样，我少了电话费，但你可以用kik和我短信，用google voice和我通话，用facetime和我视频</li>
<li>发表于微信立项前一天</li>
</ul>
<p>p104: 有自己的理念和愿景</p>
<ul>
<li>微信是“一种生活方式”</li>
<li>理念决定了你的产品的高度</li>
<li>你的态度会反映在产品的各个细节中，不可回避</li>
</ul>
<p>p105: 微信是“一个生活方式”</p>
<ul>
<li>是“个”，而不是“种”</li>
<li>微信和QQ的区别就在这里</li>
</ul>
<p>p106: QQ邮箱：常联系</p>
<p>p107: 让技术产品传达人文意识</p>
<ul>
<li>一千个人有一千种感觉</li>
<li>微信启动画面</li>
</ul>
<p>p108: “少发微信”</p>
<ul>
<li>还有哪个产品会让用户少用？（烟除外）</li>
<li>反映你对产品和用户的理解高度</li>
<li>不为营销而做。虽然它会有营销效果</li>
</ul>
<p>p109: 让欢迎页成为你的产品发布会</p>
<ul>
<li>新功能罗列是技术思维</li>
<li>不开线下的产品发布会</li>
<li>每个欢迎页都是一个故事</li>
<li>是产品中为数不多的可以表达你的感受的地方</li>
<li>让产品值得期待</li>
</ul>
<p>p110: 不听摇滚的程序员不是好的产品经理</p>
<ul>
<li>摇滚意味着反传统，人性，自由等</li>
<li>摇滚帮助找到本性的状态，这种状态，会反映在产品里</li>
<li>Pink Floyd和MJ的故事</li>
<li>“我们不会送你iPad！”</li>
<li>有与众不同的思维，做与众不同的事</li>
</ul>
<p>p111: 做人性化的广告</p>
<ul>
<li>不为广告而广告</li>
<li>来自用户的感受是最好的（很多是来自用户在微博用的原话，如“微信，让熟悉的声音骚起来”）</li>
<li>邮箱中的微信广告</li>
</ul>
<p>p112:<br><img src="/images/wechat_p112.png" alt=""></p>
<p>p113:<br><img src="/images/wechat_p113.png" alt=""></p>
<p>p114: 找最牛的合作方</p>
<ul>
<li>兔斯基</li>
<li>国家地理摄影师</li>
<li>Nike</li>
</ul>
<p>p115:<br><img src="/images/wechat_p115.png" alt=""></p>
<p>p116: 文字反映气质</p>
<ul>
<li>产品中的文字是你和用户在说话，反映了你的气质</li>
<li>清晰易懂。表明你是有逻辑头脑清晰的人</li>
<li>不讨好用户，不抬高自己，把用户当朋友</li>
<li>案例：发图片的提示文字，登陆</li>
</ul>
<p>p117: 一些避免使用的词语</p>
<ul>
<li>不用“吧”（“立即注册吧”）</li>
<li>不用“哦”（“网络很慢哦”）</li>
<li>勉强用户的句式（“还不邀请朋友”）</li>
<li>不用“成功”（“已保存成功”，有已保存失败？）</li>
<li>用“你”，不用“您”</li>
</ul>
<p>p118: 未来感</p>
<ul>
<li>视觉关键词：未来，科技，抽象，简约</li>
<li>忘记中国元素</li>
<li>抽象，还是模拟现实？</li>
<li>只有体会到简约之美，才能应用它</li>
<li>视频会话北京，该不该用蓝天白云？（luke和pony的意见）</li>
</ul>
<p>p119: 你有没有竞争对手</p>
<ul>
<li>重要的是，自己想要做什么，而不是他们在做什么</li>
<li>微信没有竞争对手，也不分析竞争对手</li>
<li>他们不是我们的产品经理</li>
<li>与其关注同行，不如关注未来</li>
</ul>
<p>p120: 作品，而不是产品</p>
<ul>
<li>作品会打败功利的产品（Steve Jobs如此评价对微软的竞争）</li>
<li>作品渴望完美</li>
</ul>
<p>p121: 工匠，而不是设计师</p>
<ul>
<li>每天优化十个细节（自己和周围人使用中遇到不便的地方）</li>
<li>你做的每个细节都是在创造，它包含了你的看法，思路，实现方法的选择</li>
<li>不空谈设计</li>
</ul>
<p>p122：做有灵魂的产品</p>
<ul>
<li>有灵魂：有机联系的结构（产品结构），有肌肉（功能），有气质（价值观），反应敏捷（速度快），理性（逻辑清晰，交互合理），谈吐（文案）</li>
<li>像人一样，是整体和谐而不精神分裂的</li>
<li>保持对产品的坚持甚至独裁才能使产品不分裂。集体决策导致平庸和各个部分的分裂。但需要集体讨论和理解他人意见</li>
<li>产品是有个性的。他可能不完美，但应该像手工艺品一样外表精致，内在和谐</li>
</ul>
<p>p123: 让个体更自由</p>
<ul>
<li>互联网产品应该让个体更自由</li>
<li>微博的评论机制改如何评价？</li>
<li>个性化长尾产品是未来走向</li>
<li>工业化满足低成本，个性化体现独特价值</li>
</ul>
<p>p124: UI篇</p>
<p>p125: UI是通过产品和用户交谈</p>
<p>p126: 禁止使用竞争对手的产品</p>
<ul>
<li>UI设计师禁止使用竞争对手产品，避免被误导</li>
<li>产品经理可以体验，但不应多用直接竞争对手产品</li>
</ul>
<p>p127: UI围绕特性，而非反之</p>
<ul>
<li>先特性，再UI</li>
<li>不因为一个好的UI创意而改变场景和特性</li>
</ul>
<p>p128: 条理清晰胜过视觉表现</p>
<ul>
<li>分类，还是分类！</li>
<li>分类体现在缩进关系中</li>
<li>条理清晰比快捷更重要</li>
<li>案例：对话输入条，一行还是两行？</li>
</ul>
<p>p129: 只有一种式样</p>
<ul>
<li>一个应用中，为保持一致，尽可能只有一个字体，一类控件，一种式样，一种背景……</li>
<li>多种表现让用户迷惑</li>
<li>尽可能用标准的界面</li>
<li>合理比个性更重要</li>
</ul>
<p>p130: 每个界面只有一个主题</p>
<ul>
<li>摄影原则：每个照片只有一个主题</li>
<li>不做二分式界面</li>
<li>突出主题</li>
</ul>
<p>p131: 每个对话框都有一个明显的默认按钮</p>
<ul>
<li>别让我思考</li>
<li>案例：发送原图令人迷惑</li>
</ul>
<p>p132: 对最常用操作精益求精</p>
<ul>
<li>滚动到最上面的自动拉取的平滑性</li>
<li>聊天背景的进化</li>
</ul>
<p>p133: 需要文字解释的功能不是好体验</p>
<ul>
<li>不要假定用户会看文字解释</li>
<li>不要假定用户会了解背景知识</li>
<li>做到不用解释就会用</li>
<li>少用tip，像膏药</li>
</ul>
<p>p134: 隐藏数字</p>
<ul>
<li>N个照片</li>
<li>N个联系人</li>
<li>78.56%下载中</li>
</ul>
<p>p135: 探索手机上的新交互</p>
<ul>
<li>手机往往在运动中使用</li>
<li>手机是肢体眼神，有更多传感器</li>
<li>案例：如何识别一个屋子里的人</li>
<li>案例：朋友圈看图的自动缩小</li>
</ul>
<p>p136: 锻炼自己的审美能力</p>
<ul>
<li>你的产品的美感不会超过你的审美能力</li>
<li>每个细节都会体现你的审美能力</li>
<li>案例：朋友圈的下拉转轮</li>
<li>案例：简单的美感</li>
</ul>
<p>p137: 谢谢</p>
<p>p138: 我所说的，都是错的</p>
<p>p139: 微信背后的产品观</p>
<ul>
<li>Allen Zhang（张小龙），2012年8月</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="2016/04/12/product-views-behind-wechat-en/">点击这里阅读英文版</a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;《微信背后的产品观》，作者，张小龙，微信之父。这个作品来自于2012年7月24日腾讯内部的一次特别讲座，用时8小时20分，PPT 180余页。除去保密部分，流出版PPT 139页。本文将PPT图文整理成长文，同时翻译发布英文版。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;文章最后是英文版链接。&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Tech" scheme="http://zhesong.info/categories/Tech/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Chinese" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Chinese/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>For Li Bai 1315th Birthday</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2016/03/07/libai-birthday-en/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2016/03/07/libai-birthday-en/</id>
    <published>2016-03-07T07:36:16.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T08:32:01.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>According to history records, Li Bai was born on January 15th (in Lunar Calendar) in 701 A.D. I checked the calendar, the birthday falls on Feburary 28 this year. I want to write an article, for my idol in boyhood, to celebrate his 1315th birthday.</p>
<p>The moment when I become fond of Li Bai happened in high school, when I realized he was also a recommended student like me.<br>The Chinese recommended students are those who have some outstanding speciality so that they are accepted by universities without the SAT of China. Thanks for Deng Xiaoping’s saying “Computer Science education should start with babies”, thanks to Shijiazhuang No.2 Middle School’s self-lead self-developped quality education, I became a recommended student. To my surprise, Li Bai was also a recommended student. The traditional way for ancient Chinese to become officers is to take the Imperial Examination. But Li Bai skipped the exam and got an offer from the Imperial Academy. He achieved that by his poem talent, recommendation by Officer He Zhizhang, and approval by Emperor Tang Xuanzong. It is like my experience such as CS competitions, recommendation by the Chancellor, and approval by the Department of Education.</p>
<p>One reason why I admire Li Bai is that he was always rich.<br>Between his graduation and government job, he spent most of the time in traveling around China. It was popular for students to travel, study and make friends at that time. During the traveling years, most likely Li Bai didn’t have job or salary. He should be well paid in the Imperial Academy, which is part of central government. Later his growth was limited there, Emperor Tang Xuanzong was very sorry and sent him away with a very generous alimony. The history named the scene “Gold gift and goodbye” (Ci Jin Fang Huan). In today’s words, Li Bai was always financially free.</p>
<p>Li Bai is willful, very willful.<br>The most famous scene is that he asked Queen Yang Guifei to prepare pen and ink for him, asked Emperor Tang Xuanzong’s closest assitant Gao Lishi to help him take his shoes off. If it is me, no matter how good I am, how careless I am, how much President Xi likes me, maybe I can ask our First Lady Peng to hand over me a pen, I probably won’t ask President Xi’s lead secretary to help with my shoes.<br>His willfulness appears in his attitude to the people in charge. And he wrote words when he left Chang-an unhappily: Why should I serve the power with lowered eyes and bent knees which makes me unhappy! (An Neng Cui Mei Zhe Yao Shi Quan Gui, Shi Wo Bu De Kai Xin Yan.)<br>His willfulness appears in his open attitude in spending money. Such attitude shows that he was highly confident and secure. Like he said: I was born to be a talent. After spending one thousand pieces of gold, I can easily make one thousand pieces more. (Tian Sheng Wo Cai Bi You Yong, Qian Jin San Jin Huan Fu Lai.)<br>A willful person is also a simple person.<br>He looks happy when he is happy. He looks unhappy when he is unhappy.<br>You can easily tell if he likes it or not.</p>
<p>Li Bai has a lot of hobbies.<br>Let’s check what he was into at age 15.<br>When Li Bai was 15, he read many special books, and can write articles as good as Lin Xiangru. (Shi Wu Guan Qi Shu, Zuo Fu Ling Xiang Ru.)<br>When Li Bai was 15, he likes swording, and won a lot in games. (Shi Wu Hao Jian Shu, Bian Gan Zhu Hou.)<br>When Li Bai was 15, he likes immortal secret, and kept traveling to look for immortal secret. (Shi Wu You Shen Xian, Xian You Wei Ceng Xie.)<br>We can see that he had a cultural hobby which was reading. His input empowered him with great output as good writings.<br>He had a sports hobby which was swording, and did well in local competitions.<br>He had a spiritual hobby which was to be immortal, and he tried hard.<br>Besides those healthy hobbies, he had another two unhealthy hobbies: fighting and drinking. Though we now know that fighting is not good, and drinking should be controlled.</p>
<p>I always believe, people should have dreams.<br>According to my observation, Li Bai had 3 dreams: the dream to be a knight, the dream to be immortal, the dream to be a president. These 3 dreams still make sense in today’s values. The knight dream is to pursue justice and world peace. The immortal dream is to pursue health and medicine improvement. The president dream is to have big impact.<br>Li Bai realized the knight dream.<br>For sure, he didn’t become immortal who never die, but he had a solid foundation as a Taoist. And he did become immortal for his poems. The readers were shocked, and cried it must be written by some immortal who was demoted from the heaven. Li Bai also felt good, and wrote words: The immortal touched my head, and taught me the way to be immortal. (Xian Ren Fu Wo Ding, Jie Fa Shou Chang Sheng.)<br>About the president dream, unfortunately, he didn’t get it. He tried really hard, but didn’t get an opportunity. Though he did get an opportunity when he was old, and the opportunity almost killed him. A widely accepted explanation is that Li Bai’s personality and speciality is not a good match to politics. What I learnt from it is that: good articles hates life winners. And people should choose a career which matches them, and it’s recommended to develop a hobby which you are really into. So you can still have fun and be happy if you are unlucky at work.</p>
<p>The most precious thing left by Li Bai is his poem.<br>The poem is beyond imagination and very powerful. It passed over 1000 years. In moments of lives of Chinese people of countless generations, it described people feelings so vividly, and made us resonated and moved again and again.<br>Following are examples. I wrote down the feeling or scene, you can come up with suitable Li Bai’s poem.</p>
<ul>
<li>I was like, I miss home. Ju Tou Wang Ming Yue, <strong>___</strong>.</li>
<li>I was like, hahaha, I am so good, your guys are so so. Yang Tian Da Xiao Chu Men Qu, <strong>___</strong>.</li>
<li>I was like, when I was travelling, I came to a big river. Huang He Zhi Shui Tian Shang Lai, <strong>___</strong>.</li>
<li>I was like, when I was travelling, I felt hungry. Ri Zhao Xiang Lu Sheng Zi Yan, <strong>___</strong>. (I know this poem is borgus XD.)</li>
<li>I was like, f*ck, I quit. An Neng Cui Mei Zhe Yao Shi Quan Gui, <strong>___</strong>.</li>
<li>I was like, I made a big deal, let’s keep drinking. Ren Sheng De Yi Xu Jin Huan, <strong>___</strong>.</li>
<li>I was like, I had a dream last night, such and such. Hai Ke Tan Ying Zhou, <strong>___</strong>.</li>
<li>I was like, I am moved, thanks so much for coming to say goodbye. Tao Hua Tan Shui Shen Qian Chi, <strong>___</strong>.</li>
<li>I was like, come on, just buy it. Tian Sheng Wo Cai Bi You Yong, <strong>___</strong>.</li>
<li>I was like, about that thing, it’s just so so. Shi Jian Xing Le Yi Ru Ci, <strong>___</strong>.</li>
<li>I was like, hi miss, you are so beautiful. Yun Xiang Yi Shang Hua Xiang Rong, <strong>___</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p>Let me stop here. Otherwise the more I wrote, the more Li Bai will hate me.<br>Happy birthday to you, Li Bai!</p>
<p><a href="2016/03/06/libai-birthday/">Click Here for Chinese Version</a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;According to history records, Li Bai was born on January 15th (in Lunar Calendar) in 701 A.D. I checked the calendar, the birthday falls 
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Life" scheme="http://zhesong.info/categories/Life/"/>
    
    
      <category term="English" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/English/"/>
    
      <category term="Writing" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Writing/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>纪念李白诞辰1315周年</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2016/03/07/libai-birthday/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2016/03/07/libai-birthday/</id>
    <published>2016-03-07T01:24:58.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T08:32:01.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>据史料记载，李白出生于701年旧历正月十六。我查了万年历，今年的2月28日。我要写一篇文章，纪念我的少年偶像，祝他1315岁生日快乐。</p>
<p>对李白好感大增，始于高中的一天，我发现李白也是保送生。<br>中国保送生，特指在某一方面有特长的高中生，可以免于高考直接被大学录取。感谢邓小平爷爷的批示“计算机教育要从娃娃抓起”，感谢石家庄二中自主学习自主发展的素质教育，我正是一名保送生。而我惊奇的发现，李白也是。传统中国知识分子的出仕之路是参加科举考试，而李白绕过唐朝科举考试，直接进入翰林院供职，靠的是诗歌特长，并由贺知章大人推荐，唐玄宗皇帝钦定。与我所经历的计算机竞赛获奖，校长大人推荐，教育部钦定，如出一辙。</p>
<p>羡慕李白另一点，就是李白一生不差钱。<br>离开学校之后，去翰林院工作之前，李白的大部分时间，是在游历祖国的大好河山，当时非常流行游学、游历。按照常理推断，这期间李白是没有工资性收入的。之后进入中央政府工作，待遇可以想象。尤其值得一提的是，因为成长空间受限要离开中央政府，唐玄宗非常抱歉的为他送行，并给了一大笔遣散费，史称“赐金放还”。用我们今天的话，李白一直处在财务自由的状态。</p>
<p>李白令人着迷，还因为他任性，非常任性。<br>贵妃磨墨，力士脱靴是一个代表性事件。如果是我，就算我再牛，再作，习大大再喜欢我，客气地请彭夫人帮我递支钢笔应该还好，可让总书记的大秘帮我系鞋带，我实在是作不出来。<br>任性表现在对权贵的态度，这情绪的爆发点，是不开心地离开长安时写的诗句: 安能摧眉折腰事权贵，使我不得开心颜。<br>任性表现在消费观上，享乐主义的背后，是极度的自信与安全感: 天生我材必有用，千金散尽还复来。<br>任性的人，通常也是简单的人。<br>高兴就是高兴，非常高兴。不高兴呢，我就是不高兴。<br>喜欢就是喜欢，非常喜欢。不喜欢呢，我就是不喜欢。</p>
<p>让人喜欢，又值得学习的，是李白全面的兴趣爱好。<br>我们看看李白的十五岁。<br>十五观奇书，作赋凌相如。<br>十五好剑术，遍干诸侯。<br>十五游神仙，仙游未曾歇。<br>15岁的李白，有一个文化爱好，读书，并且输入之后有输出，文章写得好。<br>15岁的李白，有一个运动爱好，击剑，并且在地方体育竞赛中，有不错的名次。<br>15岁的李白，有一个精神爱好，仙道，并且不辞山高路远，游历四方，一直坚持不懈的追求自己的兴趣爱好。<br>除了以上健康的兴趣爱好，李白还有两个不健康的爱好，打架和喝酒。当然，我们知道，打架不好，喝酒要适量。</p>
<p>我从来认为，人是要有理想和梦想的。<br>按照我的观察，李白有三个梦，侠客梦，神仙梦，宰相梦。其实，这三个梦放到今天也不过时，甚至很符合现代价值观。侠客梦，是追求公平与正义，维护世界和平。神仙梦，是追求身体健康和医学进步。宰相梦，是扩大个人的影响力。<br>侠客梦，李白算是实现了，学好了剑术，游历四方，打抱不平。<br>神仙梦，李白没有实现长生不老，但道家的理论和实践应该是学的很扎实。值得欣慰的是，李白成为了同时代最接近神仙的人，诗仙。读者读他的诗，都是被震撼的，惊呼，这简直是神仙写出来的，一定是被贬谪到人间的。李白自我感觉也很好，才能写出诗句：仙人抚我顶，结发受长生。<br>宰相梦，很遗憾，李白没有实现。他一直为之努力，可一直没有机会，晚年有过一次机会，可差点惹来了杀身之祸。一个广为接受解释是，李白的个性和特长，并不适合政治。而我从中学到的是，文章憎命达，并且人要选择适合自己的事业，最好还能有一项很投入的兴趣爱好，这样事业受挫还有爱好。</p>
<p>李白留给我们最宝贵的，是他的诗。<br>这些诗，充满了想象力，充满了力量，流传了一千多年。在一代代中国人的人生里，在无数个具体的瞬间，生动再现了我们的心情，给了我们一次又一次共鸣和陶醉。<br>下面，我们以填空题的形式，再重温一些。</p>
<ul>
<li>形容，想家了。举头望明月，<strong>___</strong>。</li>
<li>形容，哈哈哈，我真棒，你们都太二了。仰天大笑出门去，<strong>___</strong>。</li>
<li>形容，我在旅游，见到了一条大河。黄河之水天上来，<strong>___</strong>。</li>
<li>形容，我在旅游，饿了。日照香炉生紫烟，<strong>___</strong>。（我知道这个不是李白写的 XD)</li>
<li>形容，靠，老子不干了。安能摧眉折腰事权贵，<strong>___</strong>。</li>
<li>形容，这次牛逼大了，咱们继续喝，继续High。人生得意须尽欢，<strong>___</strong>。</li>
<li>形容，我做了个梦，如此这般，这般如此。海客谈瀛洲，<strong>___</strong>。</li>
<li>形容，太感动了，你还亲自来送我。桃花潭水深千尺，<strong>___</strong>。</li>
<li>形容，买买买。天生我材必有用，<strong>___</strong>。</li>
<li>形容，唉，那事，也就那么回事。世间行乐亦如此，<strong>___</strong>。</li>
<li>形容，姑娘，你真好看。云想衣裳花想容，<strong>___</strong>。</li>
</ul>
<p>就写这么多，不然写的越多，李白对我的恨就越深。<br>最后，李白，祝你生日快乐！</p>
<p><a href="2016/03/06/libai-birthday-en/">点击这里阅读英文版</a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;据史料记载，李白出生于701年旧历正月十六。我查了万年历，今年的2月28日。我要写一篇文章，纪念我的少年偶像，祝他1315岁生日快乐。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;对李白好感大增，始于高中的一天，我发现李白也是保送生。&lt;br&gt;中国保送生，特指在某一方面有特长的高中生，可以免于高考直接被大
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Life" scheme="http://zhesong.info/categories/Life/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Chinese" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Chinese/"/>
    
      <category term="Writing" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Writing/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Feng Tang - Young Men Idol in Modern China</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2016/02/22/feng-tang-en/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2016/02/22/feng-tang-en/</id>
    <published>2016-02-21T23:14:07.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T08:32:01.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I specially chose the Spring Festival (Chinese New Year) days to write about Feng Tang. Because I know that he must be writing a lot during this period of time. According to his description, besides the time he makes every day, he usually winds down during the Spring Festival to concentrate and write. And many of his works were finished in such periods. Another reason why I want to write about him is, I realized that Feng Tang’s popularity is reaching the position of boys’ idol in China today. I should start, right now.</p>
<p>In the past one year, I found that Feng Tang occupied the column sections of GQ China and For Him Magazine in China, and the best seller shelves in airport bookstores. He talked and laughed with Dou Wentao and Xu Zidong in Qiang Qiang San Ren Xing in Hong Kong Phoenix TV. He competed in public speaking with Luo Yonghao and piano playing with Zhao Yinyin in Sou Shen Ji, a Tencent original video series. He was mentioned and refererenced by my friends. His old and new articles were shared and liked by boys and girls in social networks. His poem were used by me and my then-GF as personal signitures:</p>
<p><em>Spring water begins to flow, and spring woods furiously grow.</em><br><em>Spring breeze from afar wafts here, but pales before my lady dear.</em></p>
<p>The main idea is that: it feels so good. How good? The spring breeze is like the girl’s finger touch on your face. I walked in the spring breeze for 10 miles. Good enough, right? Still not as good as being together with you.<br>This is Feng Tang’s poem.</p>
<p>We admire Feng Tang.<br>Among professional writers, he is the only one whose works probably won’t be mentioned during introduction, but instead, his resume will be rephrased. Even if Feng Tang never writes, he is already a successful figure under normal standards. And he achieved several successes in various domains.<br>What professions will America’s best high school students choose? Lawyers and doctors. Feng Tang completed the 8-year Doctor of Medicine in Peking Union Medical College and he specialized in Gynecologic Oncology. But he had to face deaths very often which made him sad and blue.<br>What will the Chinese top scorers and Olympics champaigns choose as majors for college? Many of them will choose the business schools in Tshinghua U or PKU, and later go to Wall Street investment banks, hedge funds or consulting firms. Mr. Feng graudated from an American business school with MBA, worked ten years in McKinsey and left as a partner. Many fans imagine that if they can take 100+ flights every year, commute between CBD and 5-star hotels every day and sometimes walk fast on 5th avenue with a decent business suit, they must confidently believe they are already successful.<br>In writing, Feng Tang’s achievements are also recognized by most people. “People’s Literature” ranked him as No.1 in the Top 20 Great Masters of the Future. And I believe that even comparing with modern writers, Feng Tang’s works will most likely be more valuable as time passes. He introduced the concept of “Feng Tang’s Golden Line”. The idea is that there is a line to divide writers to two groups based on achievements of their works. And the experts can measure writers by the line at first glance. It is like the same thing like, who are the real heros in Three Kingdoms, is someone really something, etc. It becomes very obvious to judge someone under such questions. And Feng Tang’s own works, should be obviously above the Golden Line.<br>Feng Tang is also an expert in ancient artifacts and specializes in jade which is a symbol for gentlemen in ancient China. According to his own words, he has a private motivation for this hobby which is to help him improve writing by researching how ancient people defined beauty.</p>
<p>Feng Tang like everything we like.<br>We like girls, Feng Tang likes. And he even wrote a book “Give me a girl when I was 18” which wrote our hearts out and the unrealized dreams.<br>We like drinking, Feng Tang likes. Once in a dinner with Beijing professional writers, he dranked 0.5L Chinese Liquor (Er Guo Tou) and was down. He was then performed stomach lavage in Peking Union Hospital by classmates. Those medical school classmates laughed at the miserable drunk Feng Tang, “Haha, how could you know you have such a day.”<br>We likes “bragging”, Feng Tang likes (I guess). And writing is a great approach to talk freely, big and lastly.</p>
<p>Feng Tang satisfied our imagination about life.<br>We want to make big money. He did. We want to be famous. He did, and accumulated a lot of loyal girl fans.<br>We want to travel around the world. He has been to most of the interesting places on earth, and then write to suggest places to live in.<br>We want to be immortal. He firstly achieved the successes which other people needs several life times to struggle for, and then beated the time by writing.<br>We want to be regarded as good people. He was a doctor who saved lifes. He worked hard to cure cancer, fighted at the very front line of modern medicine, for the sake of mankind’s well-being.</p>
<p>Feng Tang demonstrated noble values.<br>His various success quietly complies the “Three Immortal” believed by literati officialdom in ancient China: Li De, Li Gong and Li Yan (I will write about the concept in the future).<br>The noble values should contain the love for one’s motherland. After working for McKinsey for 10 years, Feng Tang joined one of the earlist founded state-owned companies to contribute for motherland.<br>The noble values should have dreams. Feng Tang’s dreams about the upcoming life is to use up himself as a writing genius, to see what more he could achieve, and to turn the inside feelings to words.</p>
<p>Facing the avid fans and the admiration to his life, Feng Tang sometimes has to answer some life-mentor-style questions. And he did pointed a road, a broad road. Nine years ago when he and ex-wife were interviewed by Hong Kong Phoenix TV, he said in the end, “It is actually simple. Just check what you are good at and what you should do. Then work on it really hard, and work on it happily. Don’t care about the outcomes. You will get something, for sure.”</p>
<p>Finally, many readers may raise a question: you wrote so much about him, do you Song Zhe want to be another Feng Tang?<br>Haha, of course not. I will be myself.</p>
<p><a href="2016/02/02/feng-tang/">Click Here for Chinese Version</a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;I specially chose the Spring Festival (Chinese New Year) days to write about Feng Tang. Because I know that he must be writing a lot duri
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Life" scheme="http://zhesong.info/categories/Life/"/>
    
    
      <category term="English" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/English/"/>
    
      <category term="Writing" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Writing/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>2016丙申猴年春节拜年帖 | 微信红包答谢新老读者活动</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2016/02/07/spring-festival-2016/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2016/02/07/spring-festival-2016/</id>
    <published>2016-02-07T06:38:05.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T08:32:01.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>读者朋友们，过年好！春节除夕、大年初一，凡是到宋哲国际博客《2016丙申猴年春节拜年贴》网页留言拜年和互相拜年的读者，并且已经是我的微信好友（或者我们在线下场合中有过一面之缘且我还有印象的），将留言截图微信发给我后，我会为您包一封5元的微信红包（也可以是6.66元，请往下阅读详情）。</p>
<p>常见问题<br>Q: 如何找到你的网页？<br>A: 您现在就已经在这个网页了。在网页的下方可以留言。另外输入网址 zhesong.info ，除夕和大年初一期间首页第一篇文章就会是拜年贴。</p>
<p>Q: 如何留言？<br>A: 必须使用disqus留言系统，目前支持Disqus, Facebook，Twitter或Google账号登陆，登陆后即可留言拜年，或者点击Reply其他读者的留言互相拜年。考虑到墙的因素，注册使用Disqus将是国内用户最方便的选择。</p>
<p>Q: 微信我试着登陆，总是成功不了。我用微信打不开你的链接。<br>A: 微信的Bug。请直接用电脑登陆网址 zhesong.info 应该就可以了。或者用微信右上角的用其他浏览器打开，也可以。</p>
<p>Q: 你是认真的？<br>A: 认真的，而且<a href="2016/01/13/my-credit-worth/"><em>我的信用很好的（点击读论据）</em></a>。这个答谢和推广活动我构想了一个月，征求了几位好友的意见。现在已经准备了四位数人民币的红包零钱，子弹应该是足够了。</p>
<p>其他：</p>
<ul>
<li>每人限领一次，红包5元。</li>
<li>想要一个大吉大利的 6.66元红包？当然可以啦，只需转发我的一篇你最喜欢的中文长文章（不包括拜年贴），6.66元红包包给你。</li>
<li>一定要用微信发给我留言截图。</li>
<li>我可能会因为时差或朋友聚会，不能及时回复和发送红包，请见谅。请容忍我最多12个小时的延迟，正常情况下我应该会见图立刻马上回复。</li>
<li>由于暂时我还没有歪果仁朋友玩微信，本文无英文版。</li>
<li>为避免法律纠纷，我保留对本活动的最终解释权。</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;读者朋友们，过年好！春节除夕、大年初一，凡是到宋哲国际博客《2016丙申猴年春节拜年贴》网页留言拜年和互相拜年的读者，并且已经是我的微信好友（或者我们在线下场合中有过一面之缘且我还有印象的），将留言截图微信发给我后，我会为您包一封5元的微信红包（也可以是6.66元，请往下阅
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Life" scheme="http://zhesong.info/categories/Life/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Chinese" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Chinese/"/>
    
      <category term="Writing" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Writing/"/>
    
      <category term="Social" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Social/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>中国当代男生偶像：冯唐</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2016/02/03/feng-tang/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2016/02/03/feng-tang/</id>
    <published>2016-02-03T03:39:23.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T08:32:01.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>选在春节前夕写冯唐，是因为我知道，很快他又要开始新一轮的写作了。按照冯大忙人的自述，除了平时挤时间，就是在春节期间静下来，进行创作，他的很多作品就是伴随着除夕完成的。另一个写他的原因，是我悄悄发现，冯先生的流行程度，已经上升到中国当代男生偶像的地位，我要赶紧动笔。</p>
<p>近一年来，我发现冯唐悄然占据了GQ中国，时尚·男人装的专栏版面，标志性的机场书店畅销书架；在凤凰卫视的《锵锵三人行》做嘉宾与窦文涛、许子东谈笑风生，在腾讯自制节目《搜神记》做主持与罗永浩、赵胤胤PK演讲和钢琴。他被我的朋友们时常谈起，偶尔引用。他的新旧文章被文艺女青年们转发，被有志男青年们点赞。他的诗句被我和我曾经的姑娘当做个人签名：春水初生，春林初盛，春风十里，不如你。<br>诗的大意是：这感觉真好，好到什么程度呢？春风吹来，就好像是姑娘的手，抚摸着你的脸。你就在这春风中走着，美着，一连走了十里。够美了吧？但还是没有和她在一起的感觉美。<br>这就是冯唐写出的诗。</p>
<p>我们崇拜冯唐。<br>作为作家圈唯一一个，被人介绍时不提及作品，而会被介绍简历的作家，冯先生即使不写作，也已经是世俗标准下的成功人士了，而且是跨界-多次-成功。<br>美国最优秀的学生会进什么学院做什么职业？答案是律师和医生。冯唐，协和医科大学8年临床医学博士毕业，而且是专攻妇科肿瘤的医生。但是因为治疗癌症要经常面对死亡，冯医生感到非常沮丧，心情很抑郁。<br>中国的高考状元们，奥林匹克金牌得主们，将怎样选择大学之路？他们中很多人会选择清华北大的工商管理学院，或者金融学院，将来去华尔街投行、对冲基金或咨询公司。冯先生，美国商学院MBA毕业，麦肯锡十年工作经验，做到合伙人。很多粉丝们想象，要是和冯先生一样，一年坐一百多次飞机，每天在香港和北京的写字楼和五星级酒店，西装革履，步履匆匆，不用别人恭维，自我就已经感觉是成功人士了。<br>在写作领域内，冯先生的成就也被大多数人所认可。《人民文学》评选他为“未来20大家”TOP20榜首，并且我认为和当代作家相比，冯唐的作品很可能在时间这个尺度上具有更强的生命力。他发明了“冯唐金线”，大意是作家作品的价值，存在一条金线将它们一分为二，明眼人一看即知，洞若观火。就和我们说这个人牛不牛，三国里的谁谁谁是不是英雄，有识之士一看就明白，达到就是达到了，没达到就是没达到。冯先生自己的作品，应该是妥妥地落在金线之上了。<br>冯先生还是古器物爱好者，精通古玉鉴赏，君子如玉的玉。按冯唐自己的说法，其实他有自己的私心，就是通过了解古代的人们喜欢什么，以什么为美，帮助自己在文字上的修炼。</p>
<p>冯唐喜欢我们喜欢的一切。<br>我们喜欢姑娘，冯唐也喜欢，还写了一本书，《十八岁给我一个姑娘》，写出了我们的心声，和没有实现的梦。<br>我们喜欢喝酒，冯唐也喜欢，某次在北京作家圈的饭局中喝下一斤白酒，不胜酒力，被送到母校协和医院被同班同学洗胃，不省人事的他被同学们哄笑，你也有今天。<br>我们喜欢吹牛逼，冯唐也喜欢，还有能比写作这件事能把牛逼吹的又牛又长久的吗。</p>
<p>冯唐满足了我们对人生的想象。<br>我们想赚钱，冯唐帮我们赚了。我们想出名，冯唐帮我们出了，还顺带圈了一大批忠实女粉丝。<br>我们想周游世界，冯唐帮我们把这个地球上的大多数有意思的地方都去了，还专门写文章帮我们分析哪里适合住。<br>我们想长生不老，冯唐先是达成了别人几辈子的成功，又通过文字这种方式在时间上达到永生。<br>我们想别人都说我们是好的人，冯唐悬壶济世，救死扶伤，在癌症这一医学的最前线，为了人类的福祉而奋斗过。</p>
<p>冯唐符合高尚的价值观。<br>冯唐的全面成功，其实暗合了中国古代士大夫阶层的“三不朽”价值观，立德、立功、立言。我将来也会专门写文章讲这个概念。<br>高尚的价值观，是爱国的价值观。十年麦肯锡之后，冯唐进入中国历史最悠久的国企，为中国效力，为自家稻粱谋。<br>高尚的价值观，是有理想的价值观。冯唐对未来人生的理想，就是把自己这块材料用尽，看自己在写作这件事上还能达到怎样的高度，把胸中的肿胀，化成文字，吐露出来。</p>
<p>面对众多粉丝的热爱，和对他的人生的仰视与艳羡，冯唐难免要回答一些人生导师的常见问题。冯唐还真的给我们指了一条明路，而且是真真正正宽阔的大道。九年前，他和前任老婆接受凤凰卫视的专访，在最后说道，“其实很简单，就是看自己最适合做什么，最应该做什么，然后努力去做，开开心心去做。结果怎么样不用担心，自然就会有的。”</p>
<p>最后，很多读者一定会问，写了这么多，宋哲你是不是也想做冯唐啊。<br>哈哈，当然不是，我做自己。</p>
<p><a href="2016/02/21/feng-tang-en/">点击这里阅读英文版</a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;选在春节前夕写冯唐，是因为我知道，很快他又要开始新一轮的写作了。按照冯大忙人的自述，除了平时挤时间，就是在春节期间静下来，进行创作，他的很多作品就是伴随着除夕完成的。另一个写他的原因，是我悄悄发现，冯先生的流行程度，已经上升到中国当代男生偶像的地位，我要赶紧动笔。&lt;/p&gt;

    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Life" scheme="http://zhesong.info/categories/Life/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Chinese" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Chinese/"/>
    
      <category term="Writing" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Writing/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Two Stories of My Father | So What If You Win In the Beginning</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2016/02/01/father-two-stories-en/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2016/02/01/father-two-stories-en/</id>
    <published>2016-02-01T06:15:35.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T08:32:01.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Among all the stories my father told me about him, there are two which has great beginnings for his benefits, but somehow turned to be bad things. Those two stories were often recalled by me, and I shared with many friends. Today, let’s talk about them.</p>
<p>Dad started high school in Julu No.4 Middle School, and he was like the King student there. He was the class monitor, and sports leader. Which is to say, he was the student in charge inside the building, and also the leader for sports outside the building. He gave speeches under the National Flag, and was also the star in school newspaper and radio station. Which is to say, he was not only the leader in student politics, but also a big one in media. Of course, his GPA was the highest. He was popular among classmates and favored by teachers. Everything was so good.<br>During the summer before final year, Dad was helping in our farm and met a cousin, who was the then Director of Culture Department in Julu County. Cousin asked him, “Which school are you in? How is it?” Dad said, “No.4. It’s good.” Cousin suggested, “No.4 is not so good. No.1 Middle School is the best and it’s in downtown. You should come to No.1. And I know the Director of Education Department of our county and the Chancellor of No.1 Middle School really well. Let me arrange you for the transfer.”<br>In this way, under Dad’s cousin’s arrangements, Dad transferred to No.1 Middle School for final year. But the new environment took time to get familiar, and the students and teachers didn’t know my Dad. He felt very upset. And final year was really hard, Dad’s performance didn’t recover to a good status. Then in the National College Entrance Examination of that year, Dad failed. But many of Dad’s classmates in No.4 got admitted to colleges.<br>The transfer and its effect was unforeseeable to Dad’s mind at that time. But he still appreciates Cousin’s arrangement, and his life in final year in downtown was actually very good according to his recall. Btw, by my calculation, my Mom should be in No.1 Middle School’s first grade at that time, but they didn’t know each other and just missed. Life is really magic.</p>
<p>Another story is the job assignment after college graduation. After he graduated from North China Oidfield School (now Tianjin Petroleum Vocational and Technical College), based on the then policy, Dad and his classmates would be assigned a job, start from management track, and work for North China Petroleum Administration Bureau under the Ministry of Petroleum under the State Council. Because one of Dad’s uncles was a manager there, he assigned Dad to be an office clerk in the headquarter of No.3 Oil Production Plant. For two of my father’s friends, one went to the remote base of the Plant, the other went to a more front-line place which was far away.<br>This is actually a very good career starting point. Such a job is half politics and half business. And it later became Petro China, a large state-owned energy monopoly and once the most profitable company in Asia. It is somehow comparable to Google, the internet technology giant 30 years later which I am working for. Apparently, life was more enjoyable in headquarter office compared with the remote base technician, and it was closer the power. By common sense, the single girls in headquarter didn’t need to suffer sunburn and windburn and they enjoyed the benefits of downtown. So they should be of more fashion. Of course, I mean the fashion of 1980s. My Dad once rode a bus for an hour to visit the classmate in remote base, and found he was living in a tent. The classmate in tent said that the third guy in more remote front-line didn’t even have a tent.<br>But, the turning point is coming. We later find that for national companies and government, it weights front-line working experiences and experiences in grassroot places a lot for promotions. So closing to retirement, the ranks of my father and two classmates, comparing with initial job assignments, are in reversed order. Of course, Dad’s rough career is partly due to the corruption. As low as one of his managers and one second-line manager, as high as Jiang Jiemin and Zhou Yongkang were put into jail for corruption, which I won’t talk much in this blog.</p>
<p>When I was reading Lao Zi, I thought it was too mysterious and exaggerating. It says that: <em>Danger is the next neighbour to security. Misfortune may be a blessing in disguise.</em> Now it does reflect in the two stories.<br>As we are limited by time and space, people’s minds usually cannot foresee what the good things at that time can be negative at a bigger magnitude. The then leading runners, because of their mind stereotype or the burden caused by advantages, will fall behind in the long run. This is also why, the top student in school and the one who gets the high starting salary and job, will most likely not be the most successful alumnus. (Of course, here by success, I mean it by the conventional standards.)</p>
<p><a href="2016/01/31/father-two-stories/">Click Here for Chinese Version</a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;Among all the stories my father told me about him, there are two which has great beginnings for his benefits, but somehow turned to be ba
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Life" scheme="http://zhesong.info/categories/Life/"/>
    
    
      <category term="English" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/English/"/>
    
      <category term="Career" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Career/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>父亲的两个故事 | 赢了起跑线又如何</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2016/02/01/father-two-stories/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2016/02/01/father-two-stories/</id>
    <published>2016-02-01T04:51:48.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T08:32:01.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>在我爸给我讲过的故事中，有这么两个在当时看来，都是极好极好的开局起手牌，但阴差阳错反而害苦了他。这两个故事常常被我回想起，并且讲给我的朋友们听。我们今天就从这里开始。</p>
<p>我爸的高中本来上的是巨鹿四中，彼时的他是巨鹿四中校霸般的存在。班长是他，团支部书记也是他；也就是说，在教学楼内上传下达的是他，在引领同学政治进步的具体落实上也有他；国旗下讲话是他，校报和广播站的明星也是他。也就是说，政治上的领袖是他，文化媒体界的大佬也是他。当然，学霸更是他，高一学年结束，他的各单科成绩均名列第一，在校方大红榜上的位置可想而知。同学拥护，老师器重，形势一片大好。<br>离毕业还有一年的那个暑假，在家里干农活的父亲，遇到了时任县文化局局长的堂兄。堂兄问他，“计波现在在哪儿上学呢，感觉怎么样？” 我爸说，“在四中，感觉还行。” 堂兄说，“四中不行啊，还在乡下。城里一中最好，你来一中吧。我来帮你办转学。”<br>就这样，我爸在堂兄的安排下在一中读毕业班。但是由于是新环境需要适应，同学和老师都不认识他，心理落差很大，加上毕业班学业繁重，成绩一直没有恢复到理想状态。于是那一年高考就没有考上，而四中的老同学很多在那一年纷纷考了出来。<br>转学和这之后的影响，以我爸当时的心智，是很难预见到的。事后回忆，他还是很感谢堂兄的安排，那一年在县城的生活是很优越的，很感谢堂兄。另外据我推算，那一年我妈也在一中念高一，只是他们彼此互不认识，算是擦肩而过，让人感叹命运的神奇。</p>
<p>另一件事是大学毕业分配。在华北石油学校（当时是中等专业学校，现天津石油职业技术学院）毕业后，按照当时的政策，我爸和他的同学们面临毕业分配，享受干部待遇，分配于当时的国务院石油部华北石油管理局（现中国石油华北油田）。这个时候，我爸被分配到了第三采油厂的基层采油队。而我爸在中等专业学校要好的两个同学，一个分到了第三采油厂第二分基地采油队，一个貌似分配到了同一个厂更偏远的第三分基地的采油前线。<br>这其实算是很好的一份事业起点。这样一份工作，又是国有特大型能源垄断企业，一度是亚洲最赚钱公司的中石油的前身，地位和30年后如日中天的互联网科技巨头谷歌（我所供职的公司）有异曲同工之妙。很明显，厂区环境，比分基地采油队技术员更安逸，更靠近权力中心。按常理，机关的单身员工不用在一线风吹日晒，又常年住在城里，自然也更时尚，当然，80年代的时尚。我爸有次坐车一个小时去第二分基地找同学玩，他记得同学住的竟然是帐篷，而住帐篷的同学说，那谁谁谁在更前线连帐篷都没有。<br>但是，转折来了。事后我们发现，国企和政府选拔干部的方式，非常注重一线的生产经验和基层的锻炼。临近退休，我爸和两位同学在官场上的官阶，参照当年毕业分配，呈倒序排列。按理说，就他那个对待工作的态度，要说一辈子都没有实质起色，除了个人因素，其他就不便于妄断了。</p>
<p>以前读老子我觉得玄之又玄，说什么，祸兮，福之所倚，福兮，祸之所伏。但从这两个故事来看，还真是很应验。<br>由于时空的局限性，人们的心智很难预见到对一些当下的好事，在更大的尺度下会有什么坏作用。而当前的领跑者，因为思维定式或者优势带来的负担，反而在长时间的竞争中慢慢落后。这也是为什么，一届学生中的成绩第一名，毕业时起薪最高、工作也光鲜的同学，几乎一定不会是这一届最成功的校友（当然，我这里定义成功，是按世俗标准）。</p>
<p>故事讲完了，与各位共勉。</p>
<p><a href="2016/01/31/father-two-stories-en/">点击这里阅读英文版</a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;在我爸给我讲过的故事中，有这么两个在当时看来，都是极好极好的开局起手牌，但阴差阳错反而害苦了他。这两个故事常常被我回想起，并且讲给我的朋友们听。我们今天就从这里开始。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我爸的高中本来上的是巨鹿四中，彼时的他是巨鹿四中校霸般的存在。班长是他，团支部书记也是他；也
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Life" scheme="http://zhesong.info/categories/Life/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Chinese" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Chinese/"/>
    
      <category term="Career" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Career/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>My Credit Worths 1.5 Billion</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2016/01/14/my-credit-worth-en/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2016/01/14/my-credit-worth-en/</id>
    <published>2016-01-14T06:30:28.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T08:32:01.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yang Lan onced interviewed Heavenly King Andy Lau (actor Liu Dehua), “In your 30+ years careers, is there any secret to success?” Andy Lau said, “Only one thing that I am really proud of, which is my credit.”</p>
<p>As no one won top prize of US lottery Power Ball last Saturday, it creates a record-breaking high prize which makes the lottery a positive-expectation investment and triggered a lottery madness across the US. After 10+ years, in my favorite 7-11 store, I bought a lottery ticket again. After sharing in my wechat frend circle, two friends on China trip vacations asked me to buy it for them. So I started reselling lottery.</p>
<p>I posted an announcement: “Now selling the only positive expectation lottery in history, Power Ball. Accept both domestic and international orders. $2 each, no extra fees. Give me a number, or we do it randomly. I will send out pictures after I get the tickets. I don’t take a cut, you get all the prizes if it happens. Tips is welcomed. In case I checked the wrong numbers, I won’t refund or pay your loss. I got 2 orders already!”<br>During operation, my clients send me money via wechat mobile payment, aka Hong Bao. I buy it, photo it and send the message. Usually, I will take pictures with a latest newspaper, San Jose Mercury News or USA Today, so it feels more historic.</p>
<p>Then I started promotions in my wechat groups: my college group and my high school group. I also replied a thread in my company’s misc maillist. Actually, per my colleagues’ request, I started a pool. Using Google Form for sign-up and Google Wallet for payment, all participants can share the total prizes, so everyone gets a better chance. Unfornately, it violates company policy that we cannot organize employees for gambling. So I have to stop it. During the several minutes life time of my pool, I already got 8 payments into my account, which I have to refund.<br>My global revenue is 222 USD, so I am definitely the forerunner of international lottery resales business. With 111 (for clients) + 3 (for myself) tickets at hands, I am taking over the biggest advantage facing the biggest opportunity this year.</p>
<p>In this lottery madness, almost all of my US classmates involved, almost all of my teammates bought in. It is very rare, especially for foreigners like us in US. During my visits to 7-11 and Safeway, everyone was doing it so that they don’t miss the chance to join a historic event.</p>
<p>Finally, someone in southcal Chino Hills (near LA) won the top prize, while my clients and I are not so lucky. But it is not a bad thing. Actually, most top prize winners didn’t end up well. Because easy money goes easily. I am happy that I don’t have to deal with my lawyer for the mixed relations. By law, such resales still count me as the owner, and I can only give the prize to my client as a gift. So it is double taxed.<br>Interestingly, there are 3 four-dollar prizes whose frequency is 1/38. It is very close to the theory chance published on Power Ball website: 1/38.32</p>
<p>The biggest benefits from this event is that it gives everyone a moment to rethink their dreams. Think about it, what’s your plan if you win. Among my colleagues, one said she will invite every team members to any place on the earth for vacation; another teammate said he will take the prize over 30 years, share first year’s money with team, share second year’s money with familiy, but he is not sure if he can survive the first two years’ raids. A girl said she will buy an island. A boy said he will buy the Lakers.<br>My posted plan is to be full-time blogger. By coincidence, Miss USTC Niu Niu also wants to be a full-time blogger, and she plans to buy global famous bloggers to advertise for her.</p>
<p>The biggest benefit for me is that, my credit value now raises up to 1.5 billion. Among all my clients, they do trust me not to run away with the top prize, so that they buy it from me. Yes, given a single choice between 1.5 billion and my credit, I will definitely choose my credit.<br>In this world, there are wealth which is way more valuable than money, and careers which is way more interesting than making money.</p>
<p><a href="2016/01/13/my-credit-worth/">Click Here for Chinese Version</a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;Yang Lan onced interviewed Heavenly King Andy Lau (actor Liu Dehua), “In your 30+ years careers, is there any secret to success?” Andy La
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Life" scheme="http://zhesong.info/categories/Life/"/>
    
    
      <category term="English" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/English/"/>
    
      <category term="Social" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Social/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>我的人品价值15亿美金</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2016/01/14/my-credit-worth/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2016/01/14/my-credit-worth/</id>
    <published>2016-01-14T05:40:01.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T08:32:01.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>杨澜采访天王刘德华，“出道30年，有什么成功的秘诀吗？” 刘天王说，“出道三十年，只有一件事我对自己很得意，那就是人品好。”</p>
<p>在上周六开奖失败后，美国彩票Power Ball创下历史最高奖池，使得买彩票变成了一件期望收益为正的事，引发全美购买狂潮。在我常去的7-11店里，时隔十多年，我又一次买了彩票。发了朋友圈，点赞之外零星有两个人因故回国想托我代买，于是我开始了代购。</p>
<p>我在朋友圈里发了这样一则通知：“现提供史上唯一期望收益为正的彩票Power Ball国际国内代购，两刀一个，无手续费，可自选可机选。买好后我会拍照发货，中了奖金都是你的，您看着给我包个红包就好。如果我一时手滑输错号了，不负任何法律责任。发稿前已收到两个代购请求。”<br>然后具体的操作办法是，需要代购的朋友用微信红包按当时Google公布出的汇率付给我，然后我买了之后拍照发货。一般我会把彩票放在San Jose Mercury News或者USA Today的最新报纸上拍照，这样更有纪念意义。<br>随即我开始在本科班群里和高中群进行推广，在公司内部琐事的邮件组里也参与了讨论。其实，我还应大家要求发起了一次团购，使用Google Form报名和Google Wallet付款，参与团购的人均分所购号码的奖金，从而大大提高中奖概率。不幸的是，这件事违反了公司禁止员工聚众赌博的规定，被紧急叫停。在这次团购短短几分钟的生命期里，我就已经收到了8位同事的付款，最后只能退款作罢。<br>最后，我的全球销售额是222美元，成为了名副其实的全球彩票代购领跑者。坐拥111张客户票+3张自购票的我，在今年最大的一次机遇面前，我占尽了先机。</p>
<p>这次是名副其实的购买狂潮，我几乎所有的留学生朋友都买了，几乎所有的同事也参与了，尤其是对于华人这个美国的外国人群体，是非常罕见的。在我去过的711和Safeway购票点，每个人都在买，生怕错过参与历史的机会。</p>
<p>最后开出的大奖花落南加州的Chino Hills（洛杉矶附近），我和我的客户们无缘大奖。不过想想也是好事，事实上很多彩票头奖的中奖者的人生都被毁掉了，这种钱来的快去的也快。并且我无需为复杂的法律关系而头痛，这种代购行为在法律上仍然算是我购买的彩票（尤其是对非美国没有社会保险号码SSN的购票人），然后我领奖后会按照赠与行为给我的客户，于是会被双重征税。<br>有趣的是，114张票中有三张4刀小奖（都是中了power number)，中奖率 1/38，非常接近官网公布的理论概率 1/38.32。</p>
<p>这个事件最大的好处，就是给了每个人重温自己梦想的机会。试想一下，如果你中了大奖，会有什么打算。我的同事们，有的说会请全组人去世界上任何的一个地方度假；另一位同事说会分期30年拿奖金，把第一年奖金分给同事，第二年分给家人，但是他怀疑是否能顺利逃脱前两年的抢劫与追杀。有人说要买一个小岛，有人想买下湖人队。我公布的计划是全职写博客，巧合的是中科大校花牛牛同学公布的也是要全职写博客，并且还要请全球知名博主为她的博客打广告。</p>
<p>这件事对我个人最大的好处便是，我的人品升值到了15亿美元。我的所有客户，都非常相信我在中大奖的情况下不会跑路，从而放心让我代购。不错，在15亿美元和我的人品之间，我会坚守自己的人品。<br>这个世界上，有远比金钱更有价值的财富，有远比赚钱更有乐趣的事业。</p>
<p><a href="2016/01/13/my-credit-worth-en/">点击这里阅读英文版</a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;杨澜采访天王刘德华，“出道30年，有什么成功的秘诀吗？” 刘天王说，“出道三十年，只有一件事我对自己很得意，那就是人品好。”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在上周六开奖失败后，美国彩票Power Ball创下历史最高奖池，使得买彩票变成了一件期望收益为正的事，引发全美购买狂潮。在我常去的7
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Life" scheme="http://zhesong.info/categories/Life/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Chinese" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Chinese/"/>
    
      <category term="Social" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Social/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>GitHub Poetic Remarks and Three Levels</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2016/01/07/github-three-levels-en/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2016/01/07/github-three-levels-en/</id>
    <published>2016-01-07T07:27:08.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T08:32:01.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As far as I can see, GitHub users are also experiencing the three levels described in <a href="https://zh.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E4%BA%BA%E9%97%B4%E8%AF%8D%E8%AF%9D" target="_blank" rel="external">“Poetic Remarks in the Human World”</a> by Wang Kuo-wei.</p>
<p><em>Level 1: Last night the west wind shriveled the green-clad trees. Alone I climb the high tower, to gaze my fill along the road to the horizon.</em></p>
<p>As a new user, by any chance, you registered a GitHub account. You dont know what <em>Git, Push, Pull, Pull Request</em> and <em>Repository</em> are. Just like an innocent child, you run into a beach full of colorful shells, but you cant even name the colors.<br>You are the only one among your friends to play with GitHub. Surfing around the webpages, you feel a little bit lonely and sad.<br>Facing repositories stared in 5-digit figure and IDs followed by some <em>k</em>, you sighed, “When can I create a famous repo like that? When can I grow to be a top coder like him.”</p>
<p><em>Level 2: My clothes grow daily more loose, yet care I not. For you am I thus wasting away in sorrow and pain.</em></p>
<p>You created your first <em>repo</em> to store your old naive code.<br>You created <code>your_id.github.io</code> and launched your technical blogging journey by <code>hexo</code> or <code>jekyll</code>.<br>Your first <em>pull request</em>, later your first incoming <em>pull request</em>.<br>Your first <em>issue</em>, later your first incoming <em>issue</em>.<br>You came up with an awesome idea, and thanks to <em>Google Search</em> and <em>StackOverflow</em>, you tackled one and another challenge, implemented one and another feature, and your open source project looks just like something.<br>There are 365 days in a year, and we found exactly 365 contribution tiles in your GitHub profile.<br>Others are complaining, “How can it be so hard to grow in tech?” You replied back, “Have you ever seen what is it like in GitHub on 4am?”</p>
<p><em>Level 3: I sought her in the crowd a hundred, a thousand times. Suddenly with a turn of the head, I saw her. That one there where the lamplight was fading.</em></p>
<p>Thank to <em>Time</em>, my good friend. One day, you found that your followers are some <em>k</em>, your new <em>repository</em> get 100+ watches on day one.<br>You once contributed code for <code>Apache</code>, you once implemented new features for <code>TensorFlow</code>, you once fixed bugs for <code>Linux</code>.<br>You gained some fame in Silicon Valley. Many people know you, you also know some of them. You and your friends meet online and offline, you drink and cheers, you talk and laugh.<br>In the annual QCon San Francisco Summit, you were interviewed by a blonde journalist, “Along your growing path, to whom do you want to say the biggest thanks?” The babe looks familiar, but you can’t remember. Thought for a short while, you said slowly, “Thanks my parents, thanks GitHub”.</p>
<p>P.S.</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="2016/01/05/github-three-levels/">My original Chinese version of this article</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://zh.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E4%BA%BA%E9%97%B4%E8%AF%8D%E8%AF%9D" target="_blank" rel="external">“Poetic Remarks in the Human World”《人间词话》</a> is a literature criticism book by Asian Studies Professor Wang Kuo-wei in 1910.</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;As far as I can see, GitHub users are also experiencing the three levels described in &lt;a href=&quot;https://zh.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E4%BA%BA%E9
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Tech" scheme="http://zhesong.info/categories/Tech/"/>
    
    
      <category term="English" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/English/"/>
    
      <category term="GitHub" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/GitHub/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>《GitHub词话》与三重境界</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2016/01/06/github-three-levels/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2016/01/06/github-three-levels/</id>
    <published>2016-01-06T02:39:30.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T08:32:01.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>在我看来，使用GitHub也存在如《人间词话》中的三重境界。</p>
<p>第一重境界：昨夜西风凋碧树。独上高楼，望尽天涯路。<br>作为一个小白用户，机缘巧合，你刚刚注册了GitHub的账号，还不知<em>Git，Push，Pull，Pull Request，Repository</em>为何物。懵懵懂懂，如一个单纯的小孩，来到了满是漂亮贝壳的沙滩，却还叫不出颜色的名字。<br>朋友中只有自己一个人在玩GitHub，在浏览着网页的你，心中还有淡淡的孤独与忧伤。<br>面对着被<em>star</em>过万遍的<em>repositories</em>，关注者以k计的id们，你发出一声长叹：什么时候我才能写出那样的名库，成为那样的牛人。</p>
<p>第二重境界：衣带渐宽终不悔，为伊消得人憔悴。<br>你创建了第一个<em>repo</em>，用来存放自己写过的小代码们。<br>你创建了 <code>你的id.github.io</code>，用<code>hexo</code>或<code>jekyll</code>开始了自己的技术博客之旅。<br>第一次<em>pull request</em>，第一次被别人<em>pull request</em>。<br>第一次创建<em>issue</em>，第一次被别人创建<em>issue</em>。<br>你想到了一个<em>idea</em>，在<em>google search</em>和<em>stackoverflow</em>的忠心辅佐下，攻克一个又一个技术难题，实现一个又一个<em>feature</em>，你的开源项目越来越像那么回事。<br>一年有365天，你的GitHub上竟然就有365条打卡记录，无一天中断。<br>别人在感叹，在技术上成长怎么那么难，你反问他：你见过GitHub凌晨四点的样子吗？</p>
<p>第三重境界：众里寻他千百度，蓦然回首，那人却在灯火阑珊处。<br>感谢时间这个好朋友，你有一天发现，你的<em>followers</em>也是以k计，你新开一个<em>repository</em>就引来了上百个watch。<br>你给<code>Apache</code>贡献过代码，给<code>TensorFlow</code>实现过<em>feature</em>，给<code>Linux</code>修过<em>bug</em>。<br>你在业界小有名气，很多人都知道你，你也认识很多人，你和你的朋友们在线上线下相遇，觥筹交错，谈笑风生。<br>江湖上都称呼你为大牛，在一年一度的InfoQ北京峰会上，凤凰科技一个带黑框眼镜的长发美女记者问你，“在成长为大牛的道路上，你最感谢谁？” 眼前的这个妹妹好像在哪里见过，你用拇指和食指摸了摸下巴，看着她的眼睛，缓缓说道，“感谢爸妈，感谢GitHub。”</p>
<p>附言：</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="2016/01/06/github-three-levels-en/">英文版请点这里</a>.</li>
<li>想了解更多我和GitHub的故事，请阅读 <a href="http://handsdirty.github.io/2015/12/30/my-first-pull-request/" target="_blank" rel="external">《GitHub Pull Request初体验 | 给Hexo博客留言页面添加评论系统》</a>。</li>
<li>本文第一次发表于 <a href="http://segmentfault.com/q/1010000004240527/a-1020000004255675" target="_blank" rel="external">SegmentFault</a>。</li>
<li>本文亦发表于知乎 <a href="https://www.zhihu.com/question/28976652/answer/80189926" target="_blank" rel="external">问题一</a>和<a href="https://www.zhihu.com/question/20070065/answer/80189595" target="_blank" rel="external">问题二</a>。</li>
<li><a href="https://zh.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E4%BA%BA%E9%97%B4%E8%AF%8D%E8%AF%9D" target="_blank" rel="external">《人间词话》</a>是国学大师王国维先生于1910年所著的一部文学批评著作。</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;在我看来，使用GitHub也存在如《人间词话》中的三重境界。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;第一重境界：昨夜西风凋碧树。独上高楼，望尽天涯路。&lt;br&gt;作为一个小白用户，机缘巧合，你刚刚注册了GitHub的账号，还不知&lt;em&gt;Git，Push，Pull，Pull Request，Reposi
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Tech" scheme="http://zhesong.info/categories/Tech/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Chinese" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Chinese/"/>
    
      <category term="GitHub" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/GitHub/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Playboy Weekly 2016 Special Interview on Sir. Song Zhe</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2016/01/03/annual-report-2015-en/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2016/01/03/annual-report-2015-en/</id>
    <published>2016-01-03T06:42:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T08:32:01.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With the background music of “Unforgettable Tonight” in <em>Karaoke Room 110 of Cupertino Music Channel</em>, Sir. Song Zhe and his friends welcomed the new year 2016. Later, Song’s party jumped into 5 cars parked in a row next to each other, started the engines and drove into 2016. If our Camera Boy Song happended to be there, he must have gently pressed the shutter, and saved the scene which was a 99% reproduce of the movie scene in “The Fast and the Furious”.</p>
<p>During the New Year’s vacation, we are very happy and honorabe to invite Sir. Song Zhe to Playboy Weekly for a special interview. Following is the interview notes.</p>
<p>Q: Senior Journalist Song Zhe<br>A: Honorable Guest Song Zhe</p>
<p>Q: Happy New Year! Sir. Song.<br>A: Happy New Year! Journalist Song.<br>Q: Long time no see. Our last interview with you can be recalled back to three years ago, when you were organizer and chief editor of “A Byte of Flyers: USTC CS 2008 Overseas Students Summary on Graduate School Application”. Time flies.<br>A: Yes, time flies. Three years was gone quietly. The then Student Song has got a job and started working in real societies.<br>Q: You know what. We call it “debut” in our circles. Debut early is not a bad thing actually. By the way, there are a lot of vacation days during Christmas and New Year. Did you travel?<br>A: I was mostly resting at home during vacation reading books such as “Biography of Elon Musk”, “Gui Chui Deng”, watching “Empresses in the Palace” (Zhen Huan Zhuan) and Xi Shuo Qian Long, cooking some dinners and also running. My VIP friend Honglei Liu visited me from Santa Barbara, we played video games, had hotpot, and enjoyed my second bottle of Wu Liang Ye of last year. Btw, I was learning snowboarding and went to Lake Tahoe four times. But I am still doing green lanes which is kind of slow.</p>
<p>Q: Four times! You are really hard working. Oh, I should now say congratulations for your promotion (fist closed to salute)! You achived it in just one year and three months, are there any secret tips to share? With one level up, how many people are you managing now?<br>A: Thanks (fist closed to salute back). Your news is so quick. It is the software engineer level from 3 to 4, and the next level 5 is so-called senior software engineer. Oh, still not managing people, not even close to it. The tech level promotion, is kind of like, tech track tittle which is different from the management track. To talk about experiences, I would say, hard working, and luck. Luo Ji Si Wei once mentioned, the success of 20s is that someone wants to lead and teach you, the success of 30s is that boss rely on your talents, the success of 40s is that people want to follow you, and the success of 50s is that you have many successfully former apprentices, students and followers all over the world. I am very lucky to encounter two tech leads who are very professional, graduated from noble top schools, and willing to lead and teach new comers. My boss is very powerful, he shared a lot of experiences, and knows really well about the arts of “Carrot and Stick”. My teammates are really awesome too! Actually the promotion time differences from level 3 to level 4 from case to case are just around half year. Not a big deal. Compared with the long career of dozens of years, there are many other more important skills to hone.</p>
<p>Q: Make sense. I heard that you visited China recently, any news or thoughts to share? Did you “enjoy” the fog haze (snicker …)?<br>A: Haha, not really. I chose September and October on purpose. The autumn sky is clear and the air is crisp in North China. In a place like Beijing where the polution can only be relieved by winds, it will be sunny as long as there are winds. One unfortunate thing, my visa application was checked. It’s my carelessness. I didn’t foresee any problem because my last application was so smooth. I was wondering, my background is so clear, well, don’t you know what my company is? So I went to the Embassy even without a resume. Later, I was stuck in China, under mixed feelings. You may call it a happy miserable.<br>I met a lot of people this time. I onced published my <em>agenda</em> which you can find in my Wechat friend circles. Some of the highlights are as the following:<br>My meeting with Zhiwei Qiu, an investment banker in China CITIC Bank. He found my post on attending Xiang Sheng Show in De Yun She, and contacted me saying that we should meet, but the problem is that, he will be on a business trip the next morning. I asked when he could be back. He replied he was not sure about <em>return date</em>. I said that I was not sure about my <em>departure date</em>, and we should just meet, right now. At that time, the Metro already shut down. I stopped a taxi and went to He Ping Li. Once I arrived in his apartment, I found that there was everything, but it was really messed up. So this is the scenario of people who make tons of money, but don’t even have time to enjoy life. We had great night chats, but the time was so short that we had to get up around 5am so that he could catch up the flight.</p>
<p>Q: Haha, so the story is, you tooked a taxi to a financial playboy’s home, stayed overnight, and came out 5:30am the next morning. Go ahead.<br>A: Well, it actually is.<br>Another one is my visit to Xu Zhang, my kindergarden and primary school classmate, who is also a senior analyst in Analysys (Yi Guan Zhi Ku). He is now kind of a public figure. He showed up in Beijing TV several times last year, and also accept interviews from medias to provide professional comments on industry news. He mainly focuses on mobile internet, so there was rich information in our conversations. I really learned a lot from him about our industry in Beijing.</p>
<p>Another one is very interesting, I met a hair stylist who took care of my head shaving. I am not kidding. He has been doing it for over 10 years, and can be called senior and successful in his profession. And I am really moved by his confidence and attitude. He is really handsome, and bragged that there are so many girls pursuing him. He even got meal boxes three meals a day, with no duplicates. We feel very congenial about each other. We drinked several times, and he also brought me to the nigth club in Wu Dao Kou.<br>Besides those stuff, most of my primary school and junior high school classmates are working in Huabei Oilfield or the general petrol system. My high school classmates are mostly in U.S. or Beijing. My college classmates are stilling reading PhDs, or just started working after graduate school, most of the ones who started working right after college did one job-hopping. Because of the industry, most of them are in Beijing. We talked a lot, about our stories, and the industry.<br>As time is limited, let me stop here about my China trip. I saw some more questions in your card, right?</p>
<p>Q: Ok, ok. Are your parents doing well?<br>A: They are doing great. Thank you! This time I found they are in better physical and metal statuses, so I am really happy.<br>Q: You may write a blog post about your China trip. I will be the first one to read it. It would be even better if it can be published in our magazine.<br>A: It’s so good to have a journalist friend. Please let me think about it.</p>
<p>Q: Haha. It’s because Bro. Song is so popular and love making friends. You must visited many friends or be visited by them. Can you talk about it?<br>A: Yes, I met a lot.<br>I think I am a top one who keep tight relationships with my old and remote friends. I met Kai Xing twice (Sillicon Valley and Beijing), Yu Tao twice (he came from London for business trip), Tianyu Gao (Los Angeles), Meng Lin (many video chats, severals meets in Beijing), Kaifei Chen and Qifan Pu (Berkeley), Peng Kang (San Francisco), Honglei Liu (Santa Barbara and Sillicon Valley), Shenquan Qu (several phone calls, and Beijing meet). Sigh, so many, I don’t think I can count them all.<br>I gave a lot of campus tours in our company, such as with Qiaochu Zhang (from New York).<br>Met a lot of elite colleagues and friends in internal activities, such as senior managers, self-driving car engineers, UX &amp; PM people, and many peers.<br>Made a lot of friends during fun activities.<br>Btw, one dinner was for 10 year anniversary of entrance to Shijiazhuang No.2 Middle School.<br>I also made a lot of phone calls (very effective communication), and had many meals with local friends.</p>
<p>Q: Great! Now, talk about the fun activities?<br>A: Let me see …<br>Great America, LA Auto Show, Paintball, Halloween Horror Room, Concert of Chen Xiaochun &amp; Zheng Yijian, Glass Blowing, Performing Actor Class. Several hikings, several movies. Several grilled fishes, several dim sums, many Chinese restaurant visits, several In&amp;out burgers.<br>About drinking, I had several great times last year. It’s very lucky that Chong Wang and Ming Xiao live nearby. It’s very lucky to meet friends who are willing to be drunk. People who drink must can understand my words.<br>A very successful series of activities, that we called a group of friends to watch the Voice of China. Really awesome.<br>I also organized a watching party in my company for Chinese employees to watch Beijing March. I was a little concerned when drafting the email, it sounds really bad if the Japanese colleagues know that we organized to watch Celebration March for Anti-Japanense War. So I renamed the event to be Watching Party of World War II Celebration March. Well, as China and U.S. are both victory countries, it must be ok no matter what.</p>
<p>Q: Haha, smart move. I know that you love reading. Any great books you read last year?<br>A: Books I finished reading: “Team Geek” on software developping teamwork, “Huo Zhe Huo Zhe Jiu Lao Le” by Feng Tang, “Expert Adversor Programming” about programmatic trading. To my shame, I only read 3 books last year. Accidentally, it is just one book each for IT, literature and finance. I bought tons of books, and the books I am reading should be more than 10. Hope I can finish reading more books in the coming year.</p>
<p>Q: Mr. Song, you know that our “Playboy Weekly Magazine” writes about gossips. We all know you are a romantic gentleman, can you share some personal affairs?<br>A: Haha, I know you are going to ask that. Well, let’s keep it short, it is also a protection to me. Anyway, such and such, I am availalbe again now. Yeah!<br>Q: We know there are few girls in bay area. We understand. Actually, there are many hot girls in our press. Want me to introduce? What kind of girls do you like?<br>A: Big breasts! Big breasts! Big breasts! </p>
<p>Q: Important things should repeat three times. You know something, haha. But I cannot tell the breast size in winter, they are wearing too much.<br>Well, last question. What are your new year resolutions?<br>A: New year resolutions don’t need to be many. One or two is enough. I want to be a decent blog writer. I have been desiring to do it for years. It would be really good if I can achieve it. But it is hard to start. Fortunately, I wrote one at the end of 2015, <a href="2015/12/30/my-first-pull-request/">my first blog post</a>. Now I have a writing plan of <a href="https://github.com/handsdirty/handsdirty.github.io/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;q=is%3Aissue+" target="_blank" rel="external">over 10 topics</a>. And my new domain name is coming soon. Let me see, one post a week is kind of the limit for a writer’s mental status, I should also not be quiet for over one month. There are 52 weeks a year, then let me write at least 26 blogs in 2016.<br>Q: Great! We are looking forward to it. Wish you a great success! Happy New Year!<br>A: Happy New Year!</p>
<p><a href="2016/01/02/annual-report-2015/">Click Here for Chinese Version</a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;With the background music of “Unforgettable Tonight” in &lt;em&gt;Karaoke Room 110 of Cupertino Music Channel&lt;/em&gt;, Sir. Song Zhe and his frien
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Life" scheme="http://zhesong.info/categories/Life/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Interview" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Interview/"/>
    
      <category term="English" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/English/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>《娱乐星周刊》2016新年特刊·专访宋哲先生</title>
    <link href="http://zhesong.info/2016/01/03/annual-report-2015/"/>
    <id>http://zhesong.info/2016/01/03/annual-report-2015/</id>
    <published>2016-01-03T05:46:43.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-15T08:32:01.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>在<em>Cupertino Music Channel Room 110</em>《难忘今宵》的歌声中，宋哲和他的朋友们迎来了2016的第一秒钟，一行人告别后进入<strong>连续并排停靠的五辆车</strong>，发动引擎，驶入了2016的生活。此时，如果我们的摄影师小宋在场的话，一定会按下快门，记录下这还原度99%的《速度与激情》画面。</p>
<p>趁着新年假期，我们很高兴再次请到了宋哲先生，接受我刊的新年专访，下面是采访实录。</p>
<p>Q: 特派记者 宋哲<br>A: 特邀嘉宾 宋哲</p>
<p>Q: 新年好，宋先生。<br>A: 新年好，宋记者。<br>Q: 好久不见啊，上一次采访还是三年前你策划主编中科大计算机系飞跃手册的时候，时间过得真快啊。<br>A: 是啊，时光飞逝，转眼三年。那时的宋同学，已经参加工作变成了社会人士了。<br>Q: 嘿嘿，你知道吗，我们圈里管这个叫出道，出道早是好事啊。话说，圣诞、新年假期特别多，有没有出去玩？<br>A: 这个假期主要在家休息，读书，读《Elon Musk传》《鬼吹灯》，看看《甄嬛传》《戏说乾隆》，做做饭，跑跑步。有Santa Barbara的贵客刘洪磊来访，一起打游戏，吃火锅，干掉了去年的第二瓶五粮液。哦对了，我在学单板滑雪，去Tahoe滑了四次雪，不过现在还是绿道的水平，惭愧啊。</p>
<p>Q: 四次，你也是蛮拼的呀。忘了要恭喜你高升啊（拱手抱拳），听说你只用了一年三个月，非常快，有什么职场经验吗。怎么样，现在官升一级，下面得带不少人吧？<br>A: 谢谢谢谢（抱拳回礼），你消息还挺灵通的。是我们公司技术级别的3级升4级，然后下一步5级就是所谓的高级工程师了。嗨，管什么人啊，还远着呢。技术级别的升级，怎么说呢，有点像评职称，和你们国企的升官发财还是差别很大的。要说职场经验，就是努力工作吧。然后运气也很重要的。罗辑思维曾经说，20岁有人愿意带你是成功，30岁有人愿意用你是成功，40岁有人跟你是成功，50岁桃李满天下是成功。我很幸运，遇到了非常懂行、出身尊贵、愿意指点新人的两位Tech Leads，而且老板非常给力，分享了很多经验，也懂得胡萝卜加大棒的管理艺术，同事们也都很赞。其实3到4快的慢的也就相差半年左右吧，不用太担心，对几十年的职业生涯来讲，有太多的技能更值得优化。</p>
<p>Q：有道理。听说你最近回国了，回国有什么见闻和感想吗？雾霾吸得爽不爽（坏笑）？<br>A: 还真没怎么吸（挑了一下眉毛）。我专门挑的九十月份回国的，那时候北方秋高气爽，在北京这种环保只能靠吹的地方，有风就有晴天。比较蛋疼的是，我被check了。还是怪我大意了，上一次太顺利了，我想背景这么清白这有什么可check的啊，签证官你连我们公司都不知道么。结果我连简历都没带。然后我就怀着复杂的心情滞留了下来，也算是因祸得福吧。<br>这次见了很多人，我发过行程单的，翻我朋友圈能找到。比较有意思的有这么几次会面吧：<br>去见中信投行的仇志伟。那小子看我发朋友圈在德云社听相声，然后微信联系我，说咱这老朋友得见面聊一聊啊，可惜他第二天要去重庆出差。我问你什么时候回来啊。他说<em>不知道什么时候回来</em>。我说，得嘞，我这边被check了<em>不知道什么时候走</em>，我现在就过去吧。然后那时候地铁都停了，我十一点半打了个车去的和平里。然后我去了一看，他家啥都有，但是特别乱，原来这就是那种特别忙，挣很多很多钱，但真没有时间生活的生活。我们夜聊的很开心，可惜时间太短了，由于要赶飞机，我们定了五点多的闹钟。<br>Q: 哈哈，所以这故事是，你晚上十一点半打了个车去金融高富帅家过夜，然后早晨五点半又出来的故事。你继续。<br>A: 这个，事实确实是这样子的。<br>我去望京找小学同学张旭，易观智库的高级分析师。人家也算是个公众人物，经常上北京电视台，或者接受报纸采访作为专家点评业内动态的。由于他是主要研究移动互联网的，所以和他聊天信息量极大，我对国内业内的了解还多亏了他。<br>挺好玩的是，认识了一个发型师，我主要找他剃头，别笑。十年从业经历，在他的行业里绝对算是资深和成功，那份敬业和自信还真是感染人。小伙是真帅，和我吹说追他的女生多的，一天三顿饭都有爱心便当吃，还不重样。我们很投缘，相见恨晚，性情中人，经常一起喝酒，还带着我去五道口的夜店。<br>然后，我的小学初中同学主要在华北油田和石油系统工作，高中同学美国和北京都很多，本科同学或者还在读博，读研的都是刚出道参加工作，本科毕业就工作的大多已经跳过一次槽了，因为行业关系在北京的居多。和他们交流了很多，叙叙旧啊，同行之间交流什么的。<br>由于时间关系，回国我就说到这里吧，我看你那小卡片上还有好几个问题是吧。</p>
<p>Q: 好的好的。叔叔阿姨身体还好吧？<br>A: 都挺好的，谢谢你啊。我这次回去，看他们身体和精神状态都更好了，每天忙忙碌碌的但也挺开心，看到他们过得好我就放心了。<br>Q: 你有空就把回国见闻写成博客吧，我肯定第一个来看，要是能在我们杂志社首发就更好了。<br>A: 有个记者朋友就是好啊，你容我考虑考虑。</p>
<p>Q: 嘿嘿，谁让宋哥你这人喜欢交朋友呢。去年去访问或者接待了不少朋友吧。能稍微讲讲吗？<br>A: 恩，去年见了挺多人的。<br>我觉得我算是和外地老朋友联系比较紧密的。见了邢凯两次（硅谷、北京），陶宇两次（伦敦来出差的），高天宇两次（洛杉矶），林萌（视频会议无数，北京见面无数），陈凯飞濮启凡（伯克利），康鹏（旧金山），刘洪磊两次（圣芭芭拉、硅谷），瞿神全(电话无数，北京一次）。唉，数是数不完了，而且数不全啊。<br>带朋友参观我们公司，比如见到了张翘楚（纽约）等等。<br>公司内活动认识了很多大牛和朋友，高管、无人车、其他工种等，还有很多peers（同侪）。<br>吃喝玩乐认识了很多朋友。<br>对了，今年有一顿饭还是石家庄二中校友入学十周年湾区聚会，一晃十年了。<br>然后和很多同学通过电话（很有效的沟通），和附近的朋友吃了很多顿饭。</p>
<p>Q: 赞。说说吃喝玩乐。<br>A: 这一时回想有点凌乱。<br>Great America，洛杉矶汽车展，真人CS，万圣节鬼屋，陈小春郑伊健演唱会，吹玻璃，滑雪，演员培训班体验，爬山无数，电影无数。火锅无数，烤鱼几只，港式早茶无数，中餐馆无数，In&amp;out burger几次。<br>喝，这一年喝的还蛮尽兴的，非常幸运王充、肖铭等人就住在附近，有几个愿意醉的朋友很难得的，喜欢喝酒的朋友应该能体会到我这句话。<br>然后很成功的一个系列活动是，组织了几个朋友定期在我家把中国好声音看下来了，不亦乐乎。<br>还在公司成功组织华人员工看九三阅兵，当时我发邮件还有点虚，觉得这组织看<em>抗日</em>胜利阅兵，让日本同事知道也是醉了，就把活动名改成了观看<em>纪念第二次世界大战胜利游行</em>，怎么样,美国人民和中国人民都是战胜国，而且我们反法西斯总没什么问题吧。</p>
<p>Q: 哈哈，好机智。看你挺爱读书的。去年读了哪些好书呢?<br>A: 读完的书有《Team Geek》讲软件开发团队协作的，《活着活着就老了》冯唐散文集，《Expert Adversor Programming》讲程序化交易的。惭愧，一年只读完了三本书，不过很巧，正好是IT、文学、金融各一本。然后买书无数，在读的十本也是有的，希望明年能读完更多的书。</p>
<p>Q: 宋先生，你知道，我们这个《娱乐星周刊》其实是个八卦小报。久闻宋大人风流潇洒，您，要不自己交待交待吧？<br>A：哈哈，就知道你要问这个。还是别说太多吧，对我也是一种保护不是么。总之，2015如此这般，这般如此之后，我又是available状态了。耶！<br>Q: 湾区女生少啊，我们理解。我们社里其实好多漂亮小姑娘呢，我给您介绍介绍，想要什么样的？<br>A: 胸大就好，胸大就好，胸大就好。</p>
<p>Q: 重要的事情说三遍，这你都学会了哈哈。冬天穿的多看不太出来啊。<br>那，最后一个问题，2016，新的一年有什么愿景？<br>A: 新年立志的事情不必多，一两件就好。我想把写博客这件事情做成，其实是好多年的心愿了，这件事情如果能做成的话，好处太多太大了。万事开头难，还好在2015的年底启动并写了<a href="http://handsdirty.github.io/2015/12/30/my-first-pull-request/" target="_blank" rel="external">第一篇</a>，现在已经有<a href="https://github.com/handsdirty/handsdirty.github.io/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;q=is%3Aissue+" target="_blank" rel="external">十多个选题</a>了，很快还会有独立域名上线。我想，一般一周一篇算是一个心理极限了，断更不超过一个月也是一个重要指标，然后一年有52周，我就发愿2016年写26篇博客吧。</p>
<p>Q: 太好了。我们非常期待，祝你成功啊。新年快乐！<br>A: 新年快乐！</p>
<p><a href="2016/01/02/annual-report-2015-en/">点击这里阅读英文版</a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;在&lt;em&gt;Cupertino Music Channel Room 110&lt;/em&gt;《难忘今宵》的歌声中，宋哲和他的朋友们迎来了2016的第一秒钟，一行人告别后进入&lt;strong&gt;连续并排停靠的五辆车&lt;/strong&gt;，发动引擎，驶入了2016的生活。此时，如果我们的摄影师
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Life" scheme="http://zhesong.info/categories/Life/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Interview" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Interview/"/>
    
      <category term="Chinese" scheme="http://zhesong.info/tags/Chinese/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
